[MUSIC PLAYING]
[音乐播放]
DAVID MALAN: All right, one last time.
大卫·马兰：好吧，最后一次。
This is CS50, and we realize this has been a bit of a fire hose
这是 CS50，我们意识到这有点像消防水带
over the past-- thank you.
在过去的——谢谢。
[APPLAUSE]
[掌声]
Thank you.
谢谢。
We realize this has been a bit of a fire hose.
我们意识到这有点像消防水带。
Indeed, recall that we began the class in week 0,
确实，回想一下，我们在第 0 周就开始上课，
months ago with this here MIT hack, wherein
几个月前，我们用这个 MIT 黑客，其中
a fire hose was connected to a fire hydrant,
消防水带连接到消防栓，
in turn connected to a water fountain.
然后又连接到一个饮水机。
And it really spoke to just how much information
这确实说明了在过去几个月里，我们预测会向你涌入多少信息。
we predicted would be sort of flowing at you over the past few months.
我们预测会向你涌入多少信息。
If you are feeling all these weeks later that it never actually
如果你在几周后的今天仍然感觉它并没有真正变得容易，
got easy, and with pset 1 to pset 2, pset 3 on to pset 9,
从 pset 1 到 pset 2，从 pset 3 到 pset 9，
you never quite felt like you got your footing,
你从未真正感觉到自己站稳了脚跟，
realize that it's kind of by design because every time you did get your--
意识到这其实是经过设计的，因为每当你站稳脚跟时——
every time you did get your footing, our goal
每当你站稳脚跟时，我们的目标
was to ratchet things up a little bit more
就是把事情提升一点
so that you feel like you're still getting
让你感觉你还在收获
something out of that final week.
最后一周的东西。
And indeed, that final week is now behind us.
确实，最后一周现在已经过去了。
All that remains ahead of us is the final project.
我们面前剩下的只有最后的项目了。
And what we thought we'd do today is recap a little bit of where we began
今天我们要做的是回顾一下我们的起点
and where you hopefully now are.
以及你希望现在所处的位置。
Take a look at the world of cybersecurity,
看看网络安全的世界，
because it's a scary place out there, but hopefully you're
因为那里很危险，但希望你已经
all the more equipped now with a mental model
更多地配备了思维模型
and vocabulary to evaluate threats in the real world, and as educated people,
以及词汇量来评估现实世界中的威胁，作为受过教育的人，
make decisions, be it in industry, be it in government,
做出决定，无论是在工业界，还是在政府中，
be it in your own personal or professional lives.
无论是在你个人生活中还是职业生活中。
And we hope ultimately, too, that you've walked away
我们最终也希望你能够带着
with a very practical skill, including how
一项非常实用的技能，包括如何
to program in C, how to program in Python,
用 C 语言编程，用 Python 编程，
how to program in SQL, how to program in JavaScript
用 SQL 编程，用 JavaScript 编程
in the context, for instance, of even more HTML, CSS, and the like.
例如，在更多 HTML、CSS 等的背景下。
But most importantly, we hope that you've really walked away
但最重要的是，我们希望你真正带着
with an understanding of how to program.
对编程的理解离开。
Like, you're not going to have CS50 by your side or even the duck by your side
就像，你不会永远带着 CS50 或者鸭子。
forever.
永远。
You're going to have really, that foundation that hopefully you'll
你将拥有真正意义上的基础，希望你能够
walk out of here today having accumulated over the past few months.
今天带着它离开这里，你在过去的几个月里积累了它。
And even though the world's languages are going to change,
即使世界上的语言会发生改变，
new technologies are going to exist tomorrow, hopefully,
新的技术会出现在明天，希望，
you'll find that a lot of the foundations
你会发现很多基础
over the past several months really do stay with you
在过去的几个月里真正地留在了你的脑海中
and allow you to bootstrap to a new understanding,
并让你能够快速理解新的知识，
even if you never take another CS course again.
即使你再也不学习任何 CS 课程。
Ultimately, we claim that this was all about solving problems.
最终，我们声称这一切都是关于解决问题的。
And hopefully, we've kind of cleaned up your thinking a little bit,
希望我们多少能整理你的思路，
given you more tools in your toolkit to think and evaluate and solve
给你更多的工具，让你能够更有条理地思考、评估和解决
problems more methodically, not only in code, but just algorithmically as well.
问题，不仅在代码方面，还有算法方面。
And keep this mind too.
也要记住这一点。
If you're still feeling like, oh, I never really quite got your footing--
如果你仍然觉得，哦，我从来没有真正站稳脚跟——
my footing, think back to how hard Mario might have felt some three months ago.
想想三个月前，马里奥可能有多难。
But what ultimately matters in this course is indeed, not so much
但在本课程中，真正重要的是，与其说
where you end up relative to your classmates,
你与同学们的最终位置，
but where you end up relative to yourself when you began.
不如说你相对于自己开始时的位置。
So here we are, and consider that there delta.
所以我们现在在这里，考虑一下那个差距。
And if you don't believe me, like, literally go back this weekend
如果你不相信我，就真的在本周末
or sometime soon, try implementing Mario in C. And I do
或者尽快尝试用C语言实现马里奥。我敢说
dare say it's going to come a little more readily to you.
你会更容易做到。
Even if you need to Google something, ask the duck something,
即使你需要用谷歌搜索什么，问鸭子什么，
ask ChatGPT something just to remember some stupid syntactic detail,
问ChatGPT一些东西，只是为了记住一些愚蠢的语法细节，
the ideas hopefully are with you now for some time.
希望这些想法现在已经伴随你一段时间了。
So that there hack is actually fully documented here in MIT.
所以，那个黑客事件实际上在麻省理工学院这里有完整的记录。
Our friends down the road have a tradition
我们路边的朋友有一个传统
of doing such things every year.
每年都做这样的事情。
One year, one of my favorites was they turned the dome of MIT
有一年，我最喜欢的一件事是他们把麻省理工学院的圆顶
into a recreation of R2-D2.
变成了R2-D2的复制品。
So there's a rich history of going to great lengths to prank each other,
所以，他们之间有丰富的恶作剧历史，不惜一切代价互相捉弄对方，
or even us here Harvard folks akin to the Harvard Yale video
或者我们这些哈佛人，就像上次我们看到的哈佛耶鲁视频一样。
we took a look at last time.
我们上次看过了。
And this duck has really become a defining characteristic
而这只鸭子已经真正成为了
of late of CS50, so much so that last year, the CS50 Hackathon, we invited
最近CS50的标志性特征，以至于去年，在CS50黑客马拉松上，我们邀请了
the duck along.
这只鸭子。
It posed, as it is here, for photographs with your classmates past.
它摆好姿势，就像现在这样，和你们以前的同学一起拍照。
And then around like, 4:00 AM, it disappeared, and the duck went missing.
然后大约在凌晨四点左右，它消失了，鸭子不见了。
And we were about to head off to IHOP, our friends from Yale.
我们正要前往IHOP，我们来自耶鲁的朋友们。
Your former classmates had just kind of packed up
你们以前的同学刚收拾好东西
and started driving back to New haven.
开始开车回到纽黑文。
And I'm ashamed to say our first thought was that Yale took it.
我不好意思地说，我们第一反应是耶鲁大学的人拿走了它。
And we texted our TA friends on the shuttle buses, 4:30 AM asking, hey,
我们给班上助教朋友发了短信，凌晨四点半问，嘿，
did you take our duck because we kind of need it next week for the CS50 fair?
你们拿了我们的鸭子吗？因为我们下周的CS50展会需要它。
And I'm ashamed to say that we thought so, but it was not in fact, them.
我不好意思地说，我们确实这样认为，但实际上不是他们。
It was this guy instead, down the road.
而是这个人，就在路边。
Because a few hours later after I think, no sleep on much of our part,
因为几个小时后，我想，我们大多数人几乎没睡，
we got the equivalent of a ransom email.
我们收到了相当于勒索邮件的东西。
"Hi, David, it's your friend, bbd.
“嗨，大卫，我是你的朋友，bbd。
I hope you're well and not too worried after I left so abruptly
我希望你一切都好，不要太担心，我昨晚在黑客马拉松和本学期如此成功之后就突然离开了。
yesterday night after such a successful Hackathon and semester so far.
我只是需要放松一下，去一些新地方，呼吸新鲜空气。
I just needed to unwind a bit and take a trip to new places and fresh air.
别担心，我会安全、健康、完整地回家。
Don't worry though, I will return safe, sound, healthy, home
once I am more relaxed.
一旦我放松下来。
As of right now, I'm just spending some few days with our tech friends
现在，我只跟我们的科技朋友们在一起待几天
up Massachusetts Avenue.
在马萨诸塞大道上。
They gave me a hand on moving tonight.
他们今晚帮我搬家。
For some reason, I could never find my feet, and they've been amazing hosts.
由于某些原因，我一直无法适应，他们都是很棒的主人。
I will see you soon and I will miss you and Harvard specially our students.
我会很快见到你，我会想念你，想念哈佛，尤其是我们的学生。
Sincerely yours, CS50 bbd."
你真诚的，CS50 bbd。"
So almost a perfect hack.
所以几乎是一个完美的黑客行为。
They didn't quite get the DDB detail quite right.
他们没有完全弄清楚DDB的细节。
But after this, they proceeded to make a scavenger hunt of sorts of clues here.
但在这之后，他们继续在这里进行了一场寻宝游戏。
This here is Hundredville.
这里就是Hundredville。
And so in Hundredville, they handed out flyers to students at MIT,
所以，在Hundredville，他们向麻省理工学院的学生发放了传单，
inviting folks to write a Python program to solve a mystery.
邀请大家写一个Python程序来解开一个谜团。
"The CS50 duck has been stolen.
“CS50鸭子被偷了。
The town of Hundredville has been called on you
Hundredville镇呼吁你
to solve the mystery of the-- authorities
来解开这个谜团--当局
believe that the thief stole the duck and then shortly thereafter took
相信小偷偷了鸭子，然后不久之后就带走了
a walk out of town.
走出小镇。
Your goal is to identify who the thief is, what school the thief escaped to,
你的目标是确定小偷是谁，小偷逃到了哪所学校，
and who the thief's accomplice is who helped them escape.
以及谁是小偷的同伙，帮助他们逃脱。
This took place on December 2, 2022, and took place at the CS50 Hackathon."
这件事发生在2022年12月2日，发生在CS50黑客马拉松上。”
In the days to come, we proceeded to receive a series of ransom postcards
在接下来的几天里，我们陆续收到了一系列勒索明信片
as the duck traveled, not only to MIT to Professor John Guttag 6.100B class,
当鸭子旅行时，不仅去了麻省理工学院约翰·古塔教授的6.100B课程，
which is a rough equivalent of CS50 down the road.
这相当于CS50的下一站。
Pictured there our CS50 duck with some tape on its torso.
照片里是我们CS50的鸭子，它的胸部上贴着一些胶带。
But then the duck took, apparently, a ride,
但后来鸭子明显地坐了车，
either in actuality or with Photoshop, not only there,
无论是真实地还是用Photoshop，不仅在那里，
took a tour of the Charles River in front of Harvard,
在哈佛大学前的查尔斯河上游览了一圈，
the Charles in front of Boston.
波士顿前的查尔斯河。
It went all the way over to Yale.
它一直走到了耶鲁。
We then received this postcard from Princeton
然后我们收到了来自普林斯顿的明信片
all the way over from Stanford.
从斯坦福一路走来。
Duck took a flight according to this photo here,
根据这张照片，鸭子飞了一趟，
and then saw a bit of the world as well.
然后也看到了世界的一部分。
So eventually, we received a follow-up email saying, "Hi, David.
所以最终我们收到了一封回复邮件，上面写着：“嗨，大卫。
I intend to arrive for the fair between 8:37 AM and 9:47 AM.
我打算在早上8:37到9:47之间到达集市。
It would be easier for my MIT hacker friends to bring me to the right
这样我的麻省理工学院黑客朋友们就可以更容易地把我带到正确的地方
location if there's someone waiting there with a sign that says 'Duck'."
如果那里有人拿着一个写着“鸭子”的牌子在等着。”
I'm not sure if we actually stood there with a sign holding duck,
我不确定我们是否真的站在那里，拿着一个写着鸭子的牌子，
but it turns out they came actually earlier in the morning
但事实证明，他们在早上早些时候就来了
to escape detection altogether.
以完全避免被发现。
The duck found its home and everyone lived happily ever after.
鸭子找到了家，从此大家都过上了幸福的生活。
And here the duck is again today.
今天鸭子又回来了。
But our props to our friends down the road at MIT
但我们感谢麻省理工学院的朋友们
for returning the duck safely and for going to such crazy lengths
安全地归还了鸭子，并且为了将我们列入麻省理工学院的黑客画廊而付出了如此疯狂的努力
to put us in the annals of MIT's Hacks Gallery.
将我们列入麻省理工学院黑客画廊的历史。
In fact, in exchange for this, we sent them a little package.
事实上，作为交换，我们给他们送了一个小包裹。
And without telling you what it is, you can read more
不告诉你是什么，你可以阅读更多
about this here hack that's now been immortalized
关于这个现在已被载入史册的黑客
on hacks.mit.edu at this URL here.
在 hacks.mit.edu 上的这个 URL 链接。
So maybe round of applause for our friends
所以也许让我们为我们的朋友鼓掌
down the road for having pulled that off a year ago.
为他们一年前做到了这一点。
[APPLAUSE]
[掌声]
So before we dive into some of today's material,
所以在我们深入了解今天的一些内容之前，
I wanted to give you a sense of what lies ahead as well.
我想让你了解一下未来将要发生的事情。
So this year's CS50 Hackathon is an annual tradition,
所以今年的 CS50 黑客马拉松是一个年度传统，
whereby students here at Harvard and our friends from Yale who
哈佛大学的学生和来自耶鲁大学的朋友们
will take buses in the other direction to join us
将乘坐巴士朝另一个方向来加入我们
in about a week's time for an epic all-nighter, starting roughly at 7:00
在大约一周的时间里，我们将进行一场史诗般的通宵活动，大约从晚上 7:00 开始
PM ending roughly at 7:00 AM will be punctuated
下午结束，大约在早上 7:00 结束，期间将穿插着
by multiple meals, first meal-- first dinner around 9:00 PM, second dinner
多顿饭，第一顿饭——第一顿晚餐大约在晚上 9:00，第二顿晚餐
around 1:00 AM.
大约在凌晨 1:00。
And those of you who still have the energy
对于那些仍然有精力的人来说，
and are still awake around 5:00 AM, we'll hop in a shuttle bus
并且在凌晨 5:00 左右仍然清醒，我们将乘坐班车
and head down to IHOP, the larger one down the road,
前往 IHOP，路边较大的那个，
not the one in the square, and have a little bit of breakfast together.
不是广场上的那个，我们将一起吃一点早餐。
The evening typically begins a little bit
晚上通常会以一种略带
like this with a lot of energy, the focus of which
这样的方式开始，充满了活力，重点是
is entirely on final projects.
完全在最终项目上。
The staff will be present, but the intent
工作人员会到场，但目的
is not to be 12 hours of office hours.
不是为了进行 12 小时的办公室时间。
Indeed, the staff will be working on their own projects or psets,
事实上，工作人员将忙于自己的项目或作业，
final projects, and the like, but to guide you toward and point you
最终项目等等，但目的是引导你并指引你
in the direction of solutions to new problems you have.
找到你遇到的新问题的解决方案。
And we do think that the duck, and in turn, AI, CS50.ai and other tools
我们确实认为，Duck，进而，AI，CS50.ai 和其他工具
you'll now be able to use, including the actual ChatGPT, the actual GitHub
你现在可以使用的，包括真正的 ChatGPT，真正的 GitHub
Copilot, or other AI tools which are now reasonable to use
Copilot，或其他现在可以使用的人工智能工具
at this point in the semester as you off board from CS50
在学期中的这个时候，当你从 CS50 毕业时
and enter the real world.
并进入现实世界。
Should be an opportunity for you to take your newfound knowledge of software
应该是一个机会，让你将你新获得的软件知识
out for a spin and build something of your very own, something
运用起来并构建一些你自己的东西，一些
that even maybe the TFs and myself have never dabbled in before,
甚至可能是助教和我以前从未涉足过的东西，
but with all of this now software support by your side.
但现在有了这些软件支持在你身边。
This here is our very own CS50 shuttles that will take us then to IHOP.
这里是我们自己的 CS50 班车，将带我们前往 IHOP。
And then a week after that is the epic CS50
然后一周后就是史诗般的 CS50
fair, which will be an opportunity to showcase what it is you'll
博览会，这将是一个机会展示你将在
pull off over the next few weeks to students, faculty,
未来几周内完成的事情，向学生、教职工
and staff across campus.
和校园里的工作人员展示。
More details to come, but you'll bring over your laptop or phone
更多细节将陆续公布，但你要带上你的笔记本电脑或手机
to a large space on campus.
到校园的一个大空间。
We'll invite all of your friends, even family if they're around.
我们将邀请你所有的朋友，如果他们就在附近，甚至家人也可以来。
And the goal will be simply to have chats like this
而目标仅仅是像这样进行聊天。
and present your final project to passersby.
并向路人展示你的最终项目。
There'll be a bit of an incentive model, whereby
我们会有一些激励机制，这样
anyone who chats you up about their project,
任何与你讨论他们项目的人，
you can give a little sticker to.
你可以给他们一个小贴纸。
And that will enter them into a raffle for fabulous prizes
这会让他们有机会参与抽奖，获得丰厚的奖品
to grease the wheels of conversations as well.
也为对话提供一些动力。
And you'll see faculty from across campus join us as well.
你还会看到来自校园各处的教职工加入我们。
But ultimately, you walk out of that event with this here CS50 shirt,
但最终，你将带着这件CS50 T恤离开活动，
one like it, so you too, can proudly proclaim that you indeed took CS50.
像这样一件，这样你也可以自豪地宣称你确实参加了CS50。
So all that and more to come, resting on finally, those final projects.
所以所有这些以及更多，都将最终落脚在这些最终项目上。
But how to get there.
但如何才能做到呢？
So here are some general advice that's not necessarily going
所以这里有一些普遍的建议，它们不一定适用于
to be applicable to all final projects.
所有最终项目。
But as we exit CS50 and enter the real world,
但当我们离开CS50进入现实世界时，
here are some tips on what you might read, what you might download,
这里有一些关于你可能阅读什么、下载什么的建议，
sort of starting points so that in answer to the FAQ, what now?
是某种起点，以便回答常见问题解答：现在该做什么？
So for instance, if you would like to begin
例如，如果你想开始
to experience on your own Mac or PC more of the programming environment
在你的Mac或PC上体验更多编程环境
that we provided to you, sort of turnkey style in the cloud using cs50.dev,
我们为你提供的，用cs50.dev在云端提供的一种交钥匙式的服务，
you can actually install command line tools on your own laptop, desktop,
你实际上可以在自己的笔记本电脑、台式机上安装命令行工具，
or the like.
或者类似的设备。
For instance, Apple has their own.
例如，苹果有他们自己的。
Windows has their own.
Windows也有他们自己的。
So you can open a terminal window on your own computer
所以你可以在自己的电脑上打开一个终端窗口
and execute much of the same commands that you've been doing in Linux
并执行你在Linux中一直在执行的许多相同命令
this whole term.
整个学期。
Learning Git, so Git is version control software.
学习Git，Git是版本控制软件。
And it's very, very popular in industry.
它在业界非常流行。
And it's a mechanism for saving multiple versions of your files.
它是一种保存你文件多个版本的机制。
Now, this is something you might be familiar with if still,
现在，这可能是你熟悉的事情，即使
even using file names in the real world, like on your Mac or PC--
在现实世界中使用文件名，比如在你的Mac或PC上——
maybe this is resume version 1, resume version 2,
也许这是简历版本1，简历版本2，
resume Monday night version, resume Tuesday, or whatever the case may be.
周一晚上版本的简历，周二版本的简历，或者其他任何情况。
If you're using Google documents, this happens automatically nowadays.
如果你使用谷歌文档，现在这会自动发生。
But with code, it can happen automatically, but also
但对于代码来说，它可以自动发生，但也可以
more methodically using this here tool.
使用这个工具更有条理地进行。
And Git is a very popular tool for collaborating with others as well.
Git也是一个非常流行的工具，用于与他人协作。
And you've actually been secretly using it
而你实际上一直在秘密使用它
underneath the hood for a lot of CS50's tools.
在CS50的许多工具背后。
But we've abstracted away some of the details.
但我们抽象了一些细节。
But Brian, via this video and any number of other references,
但布莱恩，通过这个视频和许多其他参考资料，
can peel back that abstraction and show you how to use it more manually.
可以剥开抽象层，向你展示如何更手动地使用它。
You don't need to use cs50.dev anymore but you are welcome to.
你不再需要使用cs50.dev，但你也可以使用。
You can instead install VS Code onto your own Mac or PC.
你可以改为将VS Code安装到自己的Mac或PC上。
If you go to this first URL here, it's a free download.
如果你访问这里第一个URL，它是免费下载的。
It's actually open source.
它实际上是开源的。
So you can even poke around and see how it, itself is built.
所以你甚至可以四处看看，看看它本身是如何构建的。
And at CS50's own documentation, we have some tips
在 CS50 自身的文档中，我们有一些提示
for making it look like CS50's environment even if longer term,
让它看起来像 CS50 的环境，即使从长远来看，
you want to cut the cord entirely.
你想要彻底断开连接。
What can you now do?
你现在能做什么？
Well, many of you for your final projects
好吧，你们很多人在你们的最终项目中
will typically tackle websites, sort of building on the ideas of problem
通常会处理网站，从问题的想法出发
set 9, CS50 finance and the like, or just generally something dynamic.
集 9，CS50 金融等等，或者只是一般性的动态东西。
But if you instead want to host a portfolio, like just your resume, just
但如果你想托管一个投资组合，比如你的简历，只是
projects you've worked on and the like, a static websites
你已经完成的项目等等，一个静态网站
can be hosted for free via various services.
可以通过各种服务免费托管。
A popular one is this URL here, called GitHub pages.
一个流行的是这里的 URL，叫做 GitHub Pages。
There's another service that offers a free tier called
还有另一个提供免费层级的服务，叫做
Netlify that can allow you to host your own projects statically for free.
Netlify，它可以让你免费静态地托管自己的项目。
But when it comes to more dynamic hosting, you have many more options.
但当涉及到更动态的托管时，你还有更多选择。
And these are just some of the most popular.
这些只是一些最流行的。
The first three are some of the biggest cloud providers
前三个是最大的云提供商
nowadays, whether it's Amazon or Microsoft Azure or Google services.
如今，无论是亚马逊，还是微软 Azure，还是谷歌服务。
If you go to this fourth URL here, this is GitHub's education pack,
如果你访问这里第四个 URL，这是 GitHub 的教育包，
they essentially broker with lots of different companies
他们本质上是与许多不同的公司合作
to give students, specifically, discounts on
为学生提供特定工具的折扣
or free access to a lot of tools.
或者免费访问许多工具。
So you might want to sign up for that while you're eligible.
所以在你符合条件的时候，你可能想注册。
And then lastly, here are two other popular third-party, but not
最后，这里还有两个流行的第三方，但不是
free services, but that are very commonly
免费服务，但它们非常普遍
used when you want to host actual web applications.
在你想要托管实际的 web 应用程序时使用。
So maybe it's Flask, maybe it's something else, but something
所以可能是 Flask，也可能是其他东西，但一些
that involves some input and output.
涉及到一些输入和输出。
Questions meanwhile-- so there's just lots of communities.
与此同时，问题-- 所以有很多社区。
If you want to keep an eye on what's happening in tech,
如果你想关注科技领域正在发生的事情，
these are just some of the popular options.
这些只是一些流行的选择。
And undoubtedly, if you have some techie friends,
毫无疑问，如果你有一些技术朋友，
they'll have suggestions as well.
他们也会有一些建议。
But you might find some of these destinations of interest.
但你可能会发现这些目的地很有趣。
Of course increasingly, will you just ask questions of software itself,
当然，你会越来越多地直接向软件本身提问，
AI, whether it's ChatGPT, GitHub Copilot, or the like.
人工智能，无论是 ChatGPT，还是 GitHub Copilot，或者类似的东西。
And then classes, we're clearly a little biased here with what's on the screen.
然后是课程，我们对屏幕上的内容明显有一些偏见。
So these aren't college classes per se, but freely available OpenCourseWare
所以这些不是大学课程本身，而是免费提供的公开课
courses that CS50's team has put together over time.
课程，CS50 的团队随着时间的推移汇集在一起。
And in a nutshell as you can infer from the suffix of each of these URLs,
简而言之，正如你从每个 URL 的后缀中推断出的那样，
if you want to learn more about Python, CS50
如果你想了解更多关于 Python 的知识，CS50
has got a free, open online class for that, or SQL, thanks
有一个免费的开放式在线课程，或者 SQL，感谢
to Carter, web and AI stuff, thanks to Brian, a games class, thanks to Colton,
卡特，网络和人工智能的东西，感谢布莱恩，一个游戏课程，感谢科尔顿，
cybersecurity, which will extend where we leave off today.
网络安全，这将扩展我们今天停下来的地方。
And then if you're more interested, not so
如果你更感兴趣，而不是
much in coding and going more deeply into software,
那么多的编码和更深入地研究软件，
but want to take a step higher level and focus more on intersections of computer
但想更上一层楼，更多地关注计算机的交叉点
science with business or law or technology,
科学与商业、法律或技术，
those two are freely available, if you're
这两者都可以免费获得，如果你
looking for something to do over January the summer or just to dabble over time.
正在寻找一些在1月、夏季或只是在一段时间内做的事情。
And there's innumerable other free resources
还有无数其他的免费资源
from other folks on the internet as well certainly too.
当然还有来自互联网上其他人的资源。
All right, so a few invitations and thank yous.
好的，所以一些邀请和感谢。
So one, after today, after we dive into and out of cybersecurity,
所以首先，在今天之后，在我们深入和退出网络安全之后，
please do stay in touch via any of CS50's online communities.
请通过 CS50 的任何在线社区保持联系。
As we start to recruit next year's team for teaching fellows, teaching
随着我们开始招募明年的教学研究员、教学
assistants, course assistants, we'll be in touch via email
助理、课程助理，我们会通过电子邮件联系
for those opportunities as well.
这些机会。
And now some thanks for the group before we then dive into here today's topic.
现在，在我们深入今天的主题之前，先感谢一下大家。
So one, allow me to thank our hosts here for giving us
所以首先，让我感谢我们在这里的主人，给了我们
access to such a wonderful, privileged space to just hold classes in,
如此美妙、特权的空间来举办课程，
the whole team for Memorial Hall.
纪念馆的全体团队。
Our thanks too, to ESS, which is the team that makes everything sound so
我们也要感谢 ESS，他们是让一切听起来如此棒的团队
good in spaces like this with music, mics, and the like, our friends,
好的空间，比如这里，有音乐、麦克风等等，我们的朋友，
of course, Wesley down the road at Changsho, where we went most
当然，路边的 Wesley 在 Changsho，我们大多数
every other Friday this semester.
这个学期每隔一个星期五都会去那里。
If you've never actually been, or if you're hearing this online,
如果你从未去过，或者你在网上听到这个，
please join our friends at Changsho show on Mass Ave down the road
请加入我们朋友在路边 Mass Ave 上的 Changsho 展览
any time you might like.
任何你喜欢的时刻。
And then especially, CS50's team-- there's quite a few humans
然后特别是 CS50 的团队，房间里有很多人类
operating cameras in the room, both here and way in back, as well as online.
在房间里操作摄像机，这里和后面以及在线上。
My thanks.
谢谢大家。
[APPLAUSE]
[掌声]
Thank you to them for making this look and sound so good.
感谢他们让这一切看起来和听起来如此棒。
And what you don't see is when I do actually screw up,
而你没有看到的是，当我确实搞砸的时候，
even if we don't fix it in real time, they very kindly
即使我们没有实时修复，他们也很友善地
help us go back in time, fix things, so that your successors have hopefully,
帮助我们回到过去，修复问题，这样你的继任者将有望
an even improved version as well.
得到一个更好的版本。
And then as well, CS50's own Sophie Anderson,
还有，CS50 自己的 Sophie Anderson，
who is the daughter of one of CS50's teaching fellows
她是 CS50 的一名教学研究员的女儿
who lives all the way over in New Zealand, who has wonderfully
住在遥远的纽西兰，她非常棒地
brought the CS50 duck to life in this animated form.
让 CS50 鸭子以动画的形式栩栩如生。
thanks to Sophie, this duck is now everywhere, including most recently,
感谢 Sophie，这只鸭子现在无处不在，包括最近，
on some T-shirts too.
在一些 T 恤上。
But of course, we have this massive support structure
但当然，我们有这个庞大的支持结构
in the form of the team.
以团队的形式。
This is some of our past team members, but who
这些是我们过去的一些团队成员，但他们
wonderfully via Zoom you'll recall in week seven,
记得在第七周通过 Zoom 非常棒地
showed us how TCP/IP works by passing those envelopes up,
向我们展示了 TCP/IP 的工作原理，通过向上传递这些信封，
down, left, and right.
向下、向左和向右。
I commented at the time, disclaim, that it actually took us
当时我评论说，声明一下，这实际上需要我们
quite a bit of effort to do that.
花费了不少努力。
And so I thought I would share as a representative thanks
所以我想代表大家表达感谢，
of our whole teaching team, whether it's Carter and Julia and Ozan and Cody
无论是谁，卡特，茱莉亚，奥赞，科迪，
and all of C50's team members in Cambridge in New Hey,
以及所有C50团队成员，在剑桥，在纽黑，
thought I'd give you a look behind the scenes at how things go indeed,
我想让你们看看幕后究竟是怎么运作的，
behind the scenes that you don't necessarily see.
一些你通常看不到的幕后内容。
So let me switch over here and hit play.
所以让我切换过来，然后点击播放。
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
[视频播放]
[INAUDIBLE]
[听不清]
[INAUDIBLE] Buffering.
[听不清] 正在缓冲。
OK.
好的。
Josh?
乔希？
Nice.
不错。
Helen?
海伦？
Oh.
哦。
[CHUCKLING]
[咯咯的笑]
[INAUDIBLE] Moni-- no, oh, wait.
[听不清] 莫妮——不，哦，等等。
That was amazing, Josh.
太棒了，乔希。
Sophie.
索菲。
Amazing.
太棒了。
That was perfect.
太完美了。
Moni.
莫妮。
[LAUGHTER] I think I--
[笑声] 我想我——
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
[声音交叠]
- Over to you, [INAUDIBLE].
- 轮到你了，[听不清]。
Guy.
盖伊。
That was amazing.
太棒了。
Thank you all.
谢谢大家。
- So good.
- 太好了。
[END PLAYBACK]
[视频结束]
DAVID MALAN: All right, these outtakes aside,
大卫·马兰：好了，这些花絮放在一边，
my thanks to the whole teaching team for making this whole class possible.
感谢整个教学团队让这堂课成为可能。
[APPLAUSE]
[掌声]
So cybersecurity, this refers to the process
所以网络安全，指的是保护我们的系统，数据，账户等等，
of keeping secure our systems, our data, our accounts, and.
的过程。
More and it's something that's going to be increasingly important, as it
而且它会越来越重要，因为
already is, just because of the sheer omnipresence of technology
已经这样了，仅仅因为科技无处不在，
on our desks, on our laps, in our pockets, and beyond.
在我们的桌子上，在我们的腿上，在我们的口袋里，以及其他地方。
So exactly what is it?
那么究竟是什么呢？
And how can we, as students of computer science over the past many weeks,
我们作为计算机科学专业的学生，在过去几周里，
think about things a little more methodically, a little more carefully,
如何以更系统，更仔细的方式思考问题，
and maybe even put some numbers to the intuition that I think a lot of you
甚至用一些数据来量化我的直觉，我认为你们很多人
probably have when it comes to deciding, is something secure or is it not?
在决定某件事是否安全的时候，可能也会有这样的直觉。
So first of all, what does it mean for something to be secure?
首先，什么是安全？
How might you as citizens of the world now answer that question?
你们作为世界公民，现在会怎么回答这个问题？
What does it mean to be secure?
什么是安全？
AUDIENCE: Resistant to attack.
观众：抵御攻击。
DAVID MALAN: OK, so resistant to attack, I like that formulation.
大卫·马兰：好的，抵御攻击，我喜欢这个说法。
Other thoughts on what it means to be secure?
还有什么关于安全的看法？
What does it mean?
这是什么意思？
Yeah.
是的。
AUDIENCE: You control who has access to it.
观众：你可以控制谁可以访问它。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so you control who has access to something.
大卫·马兰：是的，所以你可以控制谁可以访问某些东西。
And there's these techniques known as authentication, like logging in,
这些技术被称为身份验证，就像登录一样，
authorization, deciding whether or not that person,
授权，决定这个人是否
once authenticated, should have access to things.
在经过身份验证后，应该有权访问某些东西。
And, of course, you and I are very commonly
当然，我们都非常习惯于
in the habit of using fairly primitive mechanisms still.
使用相当原始的机制。
Although, we'll touch today on some technologies
虽然，我们今天会触及一些技术
that we'll see all the more of in the weeks and months and years to come.
我们将在未来几周、几个月和几年中看到更多。
But you and I are pretty much in the habit
但我们都习惯于
of relying on passwords for most everything still today.
仍然依赖密码来完成大部分事情。
And so we thought we'd begin with exactly this topic
所以我们想从这个主题开始
to consider just how secure or insecure is this mechanism and why
来考虑这种机制到底有多安全或不安全，以及原因。
and see if we can't evaluate it a little more
并看看我们是否可以更系统地对其进行评估
methodically so that we can make more than intuitive arguments,
以便我们可以提出更具说服力的论据，而不仅仅是直觉上的论据。
but quantitative compelling arguments as well.
还有定量的有力的论据。
So unfortunately we humans are not so good at choosing passwords.
不幸的是，我们人类不太擅长选择密码。
And every year, accounts are hacked into.
而且每年都会有账户被黑客入侵。
Maybe yours, maybe your friends, maybe your family members
也许是你的，也许是你的朋友，也许是你的家人
have experienced this already.
已经经历过这种情况。
And this unfortunately happens to so many people online.
不幸的是，这种情况发生在很多网民身上。
But, fortunately, there are security researchers
但幸运的是，世界上有安全研究人员
in the world that take a look at attacks once they have happened,
他们在攻击发生后会研究攻击，
particularly when data from attacks, databases, are posted online
特别是当攻击数据、数据库被发布到网上时
or on the so-called dark web or the like and downloaded
或者在所谓的暗网上或类似地方被下载
by others for malicious purposes, they can also conversely provide us
被其他人用于恶意目的，他们也可以反过来为我们提供
with some insights as to the behavior of us humans
对我们人类行为的一些见解
that might give us some insights as to when and why things
这可能让我们了解到事件发生的时间和原因
are getting attacked successfully.
被成功攻击的原因。
So as of last year, here, for instance, according to one measure
根据一项指标，截至去年，这里列出了
are the top 10 most popular, a.k.a.
最流行的前十个，也称为
worst passwords-- at least according to the data
最糟糕的密码——至少根据数据
that security researchers have been able to glean--
安全研究人员能够收集到的数据——
by attacks that have already happened.
通过已经发生的攻击。
So the number one password as of last year, according to systems compromised,
根据被入侵的系统，去年最常用的密码是
was 123456.
123456。
The second most, admin.
第二常用的密码是 admin。
The third most, 12345678.
第三常用的密码是 12345678。
And thereafter, 123456789, 1234, 12345, password, 123, Aa123456, and then
接下来是 123456789、1234、12345、password、123、Aa123456，然后是
1234567890.
1234567890。
So you can actually infer--
所以你实际上可以推断出——
sort of goofy as some of these are-- you can actually infer certain policies
尽管有些密码很愚蠢——你实际上可以推断出一些规则
from these, right?
从这些密码中，对吧？
The fact that we're taking such little effort to choose our password
我们为选择密码付出的努力如此之少，
seems to correlate really with probably, what's
似乎与可能的是，什么
the minimum length of a password required for systems?
系统要求的密码最小长度有关？
And you can see that at worst, some systems
最糟糕的是，一些系统
require only three digit passwords.
只需要三位数密码。
And maybe they might require six or eight or nine or even 10.
也许它们可能需要六位或八位或九位，甚至十位。
But you can kind of infer corporate or policies from these passwords alone.
但你光凭这些密码就可以推断出公司或政策。
If you keep going through the list, there's some funnier ones even down
如果你继续浏览列表，你会发现更有趣的一些，甚至在列表的
the list that are nonetheless enlightening.
底部也有，这些仍然具有启发性。
So, for instance, lower on the list is Iloveyou, no spaces.
例如，列表的较低位置是 Iloveyou，没有空格。
Sort of adorable, maybe it's meaningful to you.
有点可爱，也许对你来说很有意义。
But if you can think of it, so can an adversary,
但如果你能想到它，攻击者也能想到它，
so can some hacker, so much so that it's this popular on these lists.
一些黑客也能想到它，以至于它在这些列表中如此流行。
Qwertyuiop, it's not quite English, but its derivative of English keyboards.
Qwertyuiop，它不太像英语，但它源自英语键盘。
Anyone?
有人知道吗？
Yeah, so this is, if you look at a US English keyboard,
是的，所以，如果你看一个美式英语键盘，
it's just the top row of keys if you just
它只是顶部的按键行，如果你只是
hit them all together left or right to choose your, therefore, password.
把它们全部一起按下，从左到右，选择你的，因此，密码。
And then this one, "password," which has an at
然后这个，“password”，它有一个@
sign for the A and a zero for the O, which I guess I'm guessing some of you
符号代表A，0代表O，我想我猜你们中有些人
do similar tricks.
会使用类似的技巧。
But this is the thing too, if you think like you're being clever,
但这也是问题所在，如果你认为自己很聪明，
well, there's a lot of other adversaries,
那么，有很多其他的攻击者，
there's a lot of adversaries out there who are just as good at being clever.
有很多攻击者，他们同样擅长耍聪明。
So even heuristics like this that in the past, to be fair,
所以，即使像这样的启发式方法，在过去，公平地说，
you might have been taught to do because it confuses
你可能被教导过这样做，因为它会迷惑
adversaries' or hackers' attempts, unfortunately, if you know to do it,
攻击者或黑客的尝试，不幸的是，如果你知道怎么做，
so does the adversary.
攻击者也知道。
And so your accounts aren't necessarily any more secure as a result.
所以，你的帐户并不一定因此更安全。
So what are some of our takeaways from this?
所以，我们从中学到了一些什么？
Well, one, if you have these lists of passwords, all too possible
好吧，第一，如果你有这些密码列表，很可能
are, for instance, dictionary attacks.
是字典攻击。
Like we literally have published on the internet--
就像我们在互联网上发布的那样——
and there's a citation in the slides if you're curious--
如果你好奇的话，幻灯片中有一个引用——
of these most popular passwords in the world.
这些世界上最流行的密码。
So what's a smart adversary going to do when trying to get into your account?
那么，一个聪明的攻击者在试图进入你的帐户时会怎么做？
They're not necessarily going to try all possible passwords
他们不一定会尝试所有可能的密码
or try your birthday or things like that.
或者尝试你的生日或类似的东西。
They're just going to start with this top 10 list, this top 100 list.
他们只会从前十名的列表开始，前一百名的列表。
And odds are, statistically, in a room this big,
统计上，在这么大的房间里，
they're probably going to get into at least one person's account.
他们很可能会进入至少一个人的帐户。
But let's consider maybe a little more academically what we can do about this.
但让我们更学术地考虑一下，我们可以对这件事做些什么。
And let's start with something simple like the simplest, the most
让我们从一些简单的东西开始，比如最简单的，最
omnipresent device we might all have now is some kind
普遍存在的设备，我们现在可能都有一些，比如某种
of mobile device like a phone.
移动设备，比如手机。
Generally speaking, Apple and Google and others
一般来说，苹果、谷歌和其他公司
are requiring of us that we at least have
要求我们至少要有一个
a passcode or at least you're prompted to set it up
密码，或者至少会提示你设置一个。
even if you therefore opt out of it.
即使您因此选择退出。
But most of us probably have a passcode, be it numeric or alphabetic
但我们大多数人可能都拥有密码，无论是数字还是字母
or something else.
或者其他东西。
So what might we take away from that?
所以我们能从中学到什么？
Well, suppose that you do the bare minimum.
好吧，假设你只做最基本的事情。
And the default for years has generally been having
多年来的默认设置一般是拥有
at least four digits in your passcode.
至少四位数的密码。
Well, what does that mean?
好吧，这意味着什么？
Well, how secure is that?
好吧，那有多安全？
How quickly might it be hacked?
它可能被破解的速度有多快？
And, in fact, Carter, would you mind joining me up here?
事实上，卡特，你介意上来加入我吗？
Perhaps we can actually decide together how best to proceed here.
也许我们可以一起决定在这里如何才能最好地进行。
If you want to flip over to your other screen there,
如果你想翻到你的另一个屏幕，
we're going to ask everyone to go to--
我们要请每个人去——
I'll pull it up here-- this URL here if you haven't already.
我会把它拉上来——如果你还没有，这里是这个网址。
And this is going to pull up a polling website that's
这将弹出一个投票网站，它
going to allow you in a moment to answer some multiple choice questions.
将允许你一会儿回答一些多项选择题。
This is the same URL as earlier if you already logged in.
如果你已经登录，这个网址和之前的是一样的。
And in just a moment, we're going to ask you a question.
再过一会儿，我们会问你一个问题。
And I think, can we show the question before we do this?
我认为，我们可以在我们这样做之前展示问题吗？
Here's the first question from Carter here.
这是来自卡特的第一个问题。
How long might it take to crack--
破解一个四位数密码可能需要多长时间——
that is, figure out-- a four-digit passcode on someone's phone,
也就是说，弄清楚——某人手机上的四位数密码，
for instance?
比如？
How long might it take to crack a four-digit passcode?
破解一个四位数密码可能需要多长时间？
Why don't we go ahead and flip over to see who is typing in what.
为什么我们不翻过去看看谁在输入什么。
And we'll see what the scores are already.
我们也会看看分数是多少。
All right, and it looks like most of you think a few seconds.
好吧，看起来你们大多数人认为是几秒钟。
Some of you think a few minutes, a few hours, a few days.
你们中有些人认为是几分钟，几个小时，几天。
So I'd say most of you are about to be very unpleasantly surprised.
所以我想说你们大多数人将会非常不愉快地感到惊讶。
In fact, the winner here is indeed going to be a few seconds,
事实上，这里的赢家确实将是几秒钟，
but perhaps even faster than that.
但可能比这还要快。
So, in fact, let me go ahead and do this.
所以，事实上，让我继续这样做。
Thank you to Carter.
谢谢卡特。
Let me flip over and let me introduce you
让我翻过来，并向你介绍
to, unfortunately, what's a very real world problem known as a brute force
不幸的是，这是一个非常现实的世界问题，被称为蛮力
attack.
攻击。
As the word kind of conjures, if you think
正如这个词所暗示的那样，如果你想到
to-- back to yesteryear when there was some kind of battering ram trying
回到过去，当时有一种撞击器试图
to brute force their way into a castle door,
用蛮力闯入城堡大门，
it just meant trying to hammer the heck out of a system.
这仅仅意味着试图猛烈地攻击一个系统。
A castle, in that case, to get into the destination.
在这种情况下，一座城堡，是为了进入目的地。
Digitally though, this might mean being a little more clever.
然而，在数字世界中，这可能意味着要更聪明一些。
We all know how to write code in a bunch of different languages now.
我们现在都知道如何用多种不同的语言编写代码。
You could maybe open up a text editor, write a Python program to try all
你可以打开一个文本编辑器，编写一个Python程序，尝试所有
possible four-digit codes from 0000 to 9999 in order to figure out exactly,
从0000到9999的所有可能的四位数代码，以便准确地弄清楚，
how long does it actually take?
它到底需要多长时间？
So let's first consider this.
所以让我们首先考虑这一点。
Let me ask the next question.
让我问下一个问题。
How many four-digit passcodes are there?
有多少个四位数的密码？
Carter, if you wouldn't mind joining me and maybe just staying up
Carter，如果你不介意和我一起，也许就待在
with me here to run our second question at this same URL.
这里和我一起，在这个同一个 URL 上运行我们的第二个问题。
How many four-digit passcodes are there in the world?
世界上有多少个四位数的密码？
On your phone or laptop, you should now see the second question.
在你的手机或笔记本电脑上，你应该现在看到第二个问题。
And the answers include 4, 40, 9,999, 10,000, or it's OK to be unsure.
答案包括 4、40、9999、10000，或者不确定也没关系。
Let's go ahead and flip over to the results.
让我们继续翻到结果。
And it looks like most of you think 10,000.
看起来你们大多数人认为是 10000。
And, indeed, that is the case.
确实，情况就是这样。
Because if I kind of led you with 0000 to 9999, that's 10,000 possibilities.
因为如果我引导你从 0000 到 9999，那就是 10000 种可能性。
So that is, in fact, a lot.
所以事实上，这很多。
But most of you thought it'd take maybe a few seconds to actually brute force
但你们大多数人认为可能只需要几秒钟就能真正暴力破解
your way into that.
你的方式。
Let's consider how we might measure how long that actually takes.
让我们考虑一下我们如何衡量这实际上需要多长时间。
So thank you.
所以谢谢。
So in the world of a four-digit passcode-- and they
所以在四位数密码的世界里——它们
are, indeed, digits, decimal digits from 0 to 9--
确实是数字，从 0 到 9 的十进制数字——
another way to think about it is there's 10 possibilities for the first digit,
另一种思考方式是，第一个数字有 10 种可能性，
10 for the next, 10 to the 10.
下一个有 10 种，10 的 10 次方。
So that really gives us 10 times itself four times or 10,000 in total.
所以这实际上给了我们 10 自身乘以四次，也就是总共 10000 次。
But how long does that actually take?
但这实际上需要多长时间？
Well, let me go ahead and do this.
好吧，让我继续做这个。
I'm going to go ahead and open up on my Mac here, not even--
我将继续打开我的 Mac，甚至不——
not even Codespaces or cs50.dev today.
今天甚至不使用 Codespaces 或者 cs50.dev。
I'm going to open up VS Code itself.
我将打开 VS Code 本身。
So before class, I went ahead and installed VS Code on my own Mac here.
所以上课之前，我在自己的 Mac 上安装了 VS Code。
It looks almost the same as Codespaces, though the windows
它看起来几乎和 Codespaces 一样，尽管窗口
might look a little different and the menus as well.
可能看起来有点不同，菜单也一样。
And I've gone ahead here and begun a file called crack.py.
我在这里继续开始了一个名为 crack.py 的文件。
To crack something means to break into it,
破解某样东西意味着破解它，
to figure out in this case what the passcode actually is.
在这种情况下，就是要弄清楚密码是什么。
Well, how might I write some code to try all 10,000 possible passcodes?
那么，我该怎么写代码来尝试所有 10000 个可能的密码呢？
And, heck, even though this isn't quite going
而且，天哪，尽管这并不完全是
to be like hacking into my actual phone, I
像黑进我的手机一样，我
bet I could find a USB or a lightning cable, connect the two devices,
打赌我能找到 USB 或者 Lightning 数据线，连接这两个设备，
and maybe send all of these passcodes to my device trying to brute force
也许可以将所有这些密码发送到我的设备，尝试暴力破解
my way in.
我的方式。
And that's indeed how a hacker might go about doing this
这确实是黑客可能会采取的方式
if the manufacturer doesn't protect against that.
如果制造商没有对此进行保护。
So here's some code.
这是一些代码。
Let me go ahead and do this.
让我继续做这个。
From string, import digits.
从字符串中导入数字。
This isn't strictly necessary.
这并不严格必要。
But in Python, there is a string library from which
但在 Python 中，有一个字符串库，你可以从中
you can get all of the decimal digits just so I don't
获取所有十进制数字，这样我就不用
have to manually type out 0 through 9.
手动输入 0 到 9。
But that's just a minor optimization.
但这只是一个小的优化。
But there's another library called itertools,
但还有一个名为 itertools 的库，
tools related to iteration, doing things in like a looping fashion, where
与迭代相关的工具，以循环的方式做事情，比如
I can import a cross product function, a function that's
我可以导入一个叉积函数，一个允许我
going to allow me to combine like all numbers with all numbers
将所有数字与所有数字组合在一起的函数
again and again and again for the length of the passcode.
一遍又一遍地重复，直到密码长度结束。
Now I can do a simple Python for loop like this.
现在我可以像这样使用简单的 Python for 循环。
For each passcode in the cross product of those 10 digits repeated four times.
对于那些重复四次的 10 个数字的叉积中的每一个密码。
In other words, this is just a programmatic Pythonic way
换句话说，这只是一个程序化的 Python 方式
to implement the idea of combining all 10 digits with itself
来实现将所有 10 个数字与其自身结合的想法
four times in a loop in this fashion.
以这种方式在循环中重复四次。
And just so we can visualize this, let's just go ahead
为了让大家能够可视化地理解，让我们继续
and print out the passcode.
打印密码。
But if I did have a lightning cable or a USB cable, I wouldn't print it.
但如果我确实有一根闪电线或一根 USB 线，我就不会打印它。
I would maybe send it through the cable to the device
我可能会通过线缆将它发送到设备上
to try to get through the passcode screen.
尝试通过密码屏幕。
So we can revisit now the question of how long
现在我们可以重新审视这个问题，需要多长时间
might it take to get into this device.
才能进入这个设备。
Well, let's just try this.
好吧，我们来试试看。
Python of crack.py.
Python 的 crack.py。
And assume, again, it's connected via cable.
再次假设，它通过线缆连接。
So we'll see how long this program takes to run and break into this here phone.
所以我们会看看这个程序运行多长时间，以及破解这台手机需要多长时间。
Done.
完成。
So that's all it took for 10,000 iterations.
所以，破解 10,000 次迭代就够了。
And this is on a Mac that's not even the fastest one out there.
这还是在一台并非最快的 Mac 上。
You could imagine doing this even faster.
你可以想象，这个速度甚至可以更快。
So that's actually not necessarily all the best for our security.
所以，这并不一定对我们的安全来说是最理想的。
So what could we do instead of 10 digits?
所以，除了使用 10 位数字之外，我们还可以做些什么呢？
Well, most of you have probably upgraded a lot of your passwords
好吧，你们中的大多数人可能已经升级了你们的许多密码
to maybe being alphabetical instead.
可能会改为字母形式。
So what if I instead were to ask the question-- and Carter, if you
所以，如果我问一下——卡特，如果你
want to rejoin me here in a second-- what if I instead were to consider
想在一会儿加入我——如果我考虑一下
maybe four-letter passcodes?
可能是四个字母的密码？
So now we have A through Z four times.
所以，现在我们有 A 到 Z，重复四次。
And maybe we'll throw into the mix uppercase and--
也许我们会将大写和小写混合在一起——
well, let's just keep it four letters.
好吧，我们保持四个字母。
Let's just go ahead and do maybe uppercase and lowercase,
让我们继续使用大写和小写，
so 52 possibilities.
所以有 52 种可能性。
This is going to give us 52 times 52 times 52 times 52.
这将给我们 52 乘以 52 乘以 52 乘以 52。
And anyone want to ballpark the math here,
有人想在这里估计一下数学结果吗，
how many possible four-letter passcodes are there, roughly?
大约有多少个可能的四字母密码？
7 million, yeah, so roughly 7 million, which is way bigger than 10,000.
700 万，是的，大约 700 万，这远大于 10,000。
So, oh, I spoiled this, didn't I?
所以，哦，我剧透了，不是吗？
Can you flip over?
你可以翻页吗？
So how many four-letter passcodes are there?
那么，有多少个四字母密码呢？
It seems that most of you, 93% of you, in fact, got the answer right.
看起来，你们中大多数人，事实上 93% 的人，都答对了。
Those of you who are changing your answer-- there
那些正在改变答案的人——这里
we go, no, definitely not that.
我们去，不，绝对不是那样。
So, anyhow, I screwed up.
所以，无论如何，我搞砸了。
Order of operations matters in computing and, indeed, including lectures.
运算顺序在计算中很重要，实际上，包括讲座也是如此。
So 7 million, so the segue I wanted to make
所以是 700 万，所以我想说的是
is, OK, how long does that actually take to implement in code?
就是，好的，这实际上需要多长时间才能在代码中实现？
Well, let me just tweak our code here a little bit.
好吧，让我稍微调整一下我们的代码。
Let me go ahead and go back into the VS Code on my Mac in which I
让我回到我的 Mac 上的 VS Code 中，我在其中
had the same code as before.
有和之前一样的代码。
So let me shrink my terminal window, go back to the code from which I began.
所以让我缩小我的终端窗口，回到我开始使用的代码。
And let's just actually make a simple change.
让我们只做个简单的改动。
Let me go ahead and simply change digits to something called ASCII letters.
让我继续并将 digits 更改为称为 ASCII 字母的东西。
And this too is just a time saving technique.
这也只是一个节省时间的技巧。
So I don't have to type out A through Z and uppercase and lowercase like 52
所以我不必像 52 次那样把 A 到 Z 以及大小写都打出来
total times.
总共。
And so I'm going to change digits to ASCII letters.
所以我要将 digits 更改为 ASCII 字母。
And we'll get a quantitative sense of how long this takes.
我们将会定量地了解这需要多长时间。
So Python of crack.py, here's how long it takes
所以 Python 的 crack.py，这是它需要的时间
to go through 7 million possibilities.
遍历 700 万种可能性。
All right, clearly slower because we haven't seen the end of the list yet.
好吧，显然慢多了，因为我们还没有看到列表的结尾。
And you can see we're going through all of the lowercase letters here.
你可以看到我们正在遍历这里的所有小写字母。
We're about to hit Z. But now we're going through the uppercase letters.
我们马上就要到 Z 了。但现在我们正在遍历大写字母。
So it looks like the answer this time is going to be a few seconds, indeed.
所以看起来这次答案应该是几秒钟，的确。
But definitely less than a minute would seem, at least
但至少看起来应该不到一分钟
on this particular computer.
在这台特定的电脑上。
So odds are if I'm the adversary and I've
所以如果我是攻击者，而且我
plugged this phone into someone's device-- maybe
把这部手机插到了某人的设备上 - 也许
I'm not here in a lecture, but in Starbucks or an airport
我不是在课堂上，而是在星巴克或机场
or anywhere where I have physical opportunity to grab that device
或者任何我可以接触到那个设备的地方
and plug a cable in-- it's not going to take long to hack into that device
然后插入一根线 - 侵入那台设备不会花很长时间
either.
也是。
So what might be better than just digits and letters from the real world?
那么，还有什么比现实世界中的数字和字母更好呢？
So add in some punctuation, which like almost every website
所以添加一些标点符号，几乎每个网站都
requires that we do.
要求我们这样做。
Well, if we want to add punctuation into the mix, if I can get this segue
好吧，如果我们想把标点符号加进去，如果我能把这个过渡
correct so that we can now ask Carter one last time,
说对了，我们现在就可以最后一次问卡特了，
how many four-character passcodes are possible where a character is
有多少种可能的四位数密码，其中一个字符是
an uppercase or lowercase letter or a decimal digit or a punctuation symbol?
大写或小写字母，或者十进制数字，或者标点符号？
If you go to your device now, you'll see--
如果你现在看看你的设备，你会看到 -
if we want to flip over to the screen--
如果我们想切换到屏幕 -
these possibilities.
这些可能性。
There's a million, maybe, a billion, a trillion, a quadrillion,
可能有一百万，也许十亿，万亿，千万亿，
or a quintillion when it comes to a-- oh, wrong question.
或者一千万亿，当涉及到 - 哦，问错了。
Wow, we're new here, OK.
哇，我们还是新手，好的。
OK, we're going to escalate things here.
好的，我们要在这里升级一下。
How many eight-character passcodes are possible?
有多少种可能的八位数密码？
We're going to make things more secure, even though I said four.
我们要让它更安全，尽管我说过是四位数。
We're now making it more secure to eight.
我们现在把它改为八位数，更安全。
All right, you want to flip over to the chart?
好的，你想翻到图表吗？
All right, so it looks like most of you are now
好的，看起来你们大多数人现在
erring on the side of quintillion or quadrillion.
都倾向于五百万亿或万亿。
1% of you still said million, even though there's definitely more
你们中 1% 仍然说百万，尽管肯定比之前
than there were a moment ago.
多得多。
But that's OK.
但没关系。
So quadrillion-- quintillion is still winning.
所以万亿，五百万亿仍然是赢家。
And I think if we go and reveal this, with the math,
我认为如果我们去揭示这个，用数学，
you should be doing is 94 to the 4th power.
你应该做的是 94 的 4 次方。
Because there's 26 plus 26 plus 10 plus some more digits,
因为有 26 加 26 加 10 以及一些其他的数字，
some punctuation digits in there as well.
还有一些标点符号。
So it's actually, oh, this is the other example, isn't it?
所以实际上，哦，这是另一个例子，不是吗？
This is embarrassing.
真令人尴尬。
All right, we had a good run in the past nine weeks instead.
好吧，我们过去九周还不错。
All right, so if you were curious as to how many four-character passwords are
好的，如果你好奇有多少个四位字符的密码
possible, it's 78 million.
是可能的，答案是 7800 万。
But that's not the question at hand.
但这不是现在的问题。
The question at hand was, how many eight character passcodes are there?
现在的问题是，有多少个八位字符的密码？
And in this case, the math you would be doing
在这种情况下，你应该做的数学运算
is 94 to the 8th power, which is a really big number.
是 94 的 8 次方，这是一个非常大的数字。
And, in fact, it's this number here, which
事实上，就是这里这个数字，
is roughly 6 quadrillion possibilities.
大约有 6 万亿种可能性。
Now, I could go about actually doing this in code here.
现在，我可以在这里用代码来做这件事。
So let me actually, for a final flourish,
所以让我实际操作一下，作为最后的点缀，
let me open up VS Code one last time here.
让我最后一次打开 VS Code。
And in VS Code, I'm going to go ahead and shrink my terminal window,
在 VS Code 中，我将缩小我的终端窗口，
go back into the code, and I'm going to import not just ASCII letters, not just
回到代码，我将导入的不只是 ASCII 字母，也不只是
digits, but punctuation as well, which is
数字，还有标点符号，它们是
going to give me like 32 punctuation symbols
将会给我大约 32 个标点符号
from a typical US English keyboard.
来自典型的美国英语键盘。
And I'm going to go ahead and just concatenate them all together in one
我将把它们全部连接在一起，形成一个
big list by using the plus operator in Python
大列表，使用 Python 中的加号运算符
to plus in both digits and punctuation.
将数字和标点符号加起来。
And I'm going to change the 4 to an 8.
我将把 4 改为 8。
So this now, it's what four actual lines of code
所以现在，就是这四行代码，
is, all it takes for an adversary to whip up some code,
这就是攻击者编制一些代码所需的一切，
find a cable as step two, and hack into a phone that
第二步是找到一根数据线，然后黑进一部手机，
even has eight-character passcodes.
即使它有八位字符的密码。
Let me enlarge in my terminal window here, run
让我放大我的终端窗口，运行
for a final time Python of crack.py.
最后一次运行 crack.py 的 Python 代码。
And this I'll actually leave running for some time.
我将让它运行一段时间。
Because you can get already sort of a palpable feel of how much slower it
因为你已经可以感觉到它慢了多少，
is-- because these characters clearly haven't moved--
因为这些字符明显没有移动，
how long it's going to take.
要花多长时间。
We might actually do-- need to do a bit more math.
我们可能需要做更多的数学运算。
Because doing just four-digit passcodes was super fast.
因为仅仅破解四位数字密码非常快。
Doing four-letter passcodes was slower, but still under a minute.
破解四位字母密码比较慢，但仍然不到一分钟。
We'll see maybe in time how long this actually runs for.
我们会看到它到底要运行多长时间。
But this clearly seems to be better, at least for some definition of better.
但这显然更好，至少从某种意义上说。
But it should hopefully not be that easy to hack into a system.
但是，希望黑进系统不会那么容易。
What does your own device probably do to defend against that brute force attack?
你的设备可能做了什么来防御这种暴力攻击？
Yeah.
是的。
AUDIENCE: Gives you a limited number of tries.
观众：给你有限的尝试次数。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so it gives you a limited number of tries.
大卫·马兰：是的，所以它会给你有限的尝试次数。
So odds are, at least once in your life, you've somehow locked yourself out
所以很有可能，你至少曾经有一次把自己锁在门外
of a device, typically after typing your passcode more than 10 times
设备之外，通常是在输入密码超过10次之后
or 10 attempts or maybe it's your siblings or your roommate's phone
或者10次尝试，或者可能是你兄弟姐妹或者室友的手机
that you realize this is a feature of iPhones and Android devices as well.
你会意识到，这确实是 iPhone 和安卓设备的一个功能。
But here's a screenshot of what an iPhone might
但这里是一张 iPhone 可能的截图
do if you do try to input the wrong passcode maybe 10 or so times.
如果你尝试输入错误密码大约 10 次左右，就会发生的事情。
Notice that it's really telling you to try again in one minute.
注意，它真的在告诉你一分钟后重新尝试。
So this isn't fundamentally changing what the adversary can do.
所以这并没有从根本上改变对手可以做的事情。
The adversary can absolutely use those same four lines of code with a cable
对手完全可以使用这相同的四行代码，使用一根数据线
and try to hack into your device.
尝试黑进你的设备。
But what has this just done?
但这做到了什么呢？
It's significantly increased the cost to the adversary,
它显著提高了对手的成本，
where the cost might be measured in sheer number amount of time--
成本可以用纯粹的时间来衡量——
like minutes, seconds, hours, days, or beyond.
比如分钟、秒、小时、天，甚至更久。
Maybe it's increased the cost in the sense of risk.
也许它从风险的角度提高了成本。
Why?
为什么？
Because if this were like a movie incarnation of this
因为如果这就像这部电影中的情节一样
and the adversary has just plugged into the phone
而对手刚刚连接到手机上
and is kind of creepily looking around until you come back,
而且一直在诡异地环顾四周，直到你回来，
it's going to take way too long for them to safely get away with that,
他们想要安全地逃脱，这需要太长的时间了，
assuming your passcode is not 123456, it's
假设你的密码不是123456，它
somewhere in the middle of that massive search space.
在这个巨大的搜索空间中。
So this just kind of fundamentally raises the bar to the adversary.
所以这从根本上提高了对手的门槛。
And that's one of the biggest takeaways of cybersecurity in general.
这通常是网络安全最主要的启示之一。
It's completely naive to think in terms of absolute security
认为绝对安全是十分幼稚的
or to even say a sentence like "my website is secure" or even
或者说诸如“我的网站很安全”这样的话，甚至
"my home is physically secure."
“我的家是物理安全的。”
Why?
为什么？
Well, for a couple of reasons, like, one, an adversary
嗯，有几个原因，比如，第一个原因是，对手
with enough time, energy, motivation, or resources
有足够的时间、精力、动力或资源
can surely get into most any system and can surely get into most any home.
就一定能够进入大多数系统，也一定能够进入大多数房屋。
But the other thing to consider, unfortunately,
但不幸的是，还有另一个需要考虑的事情，
that if we're the good people in this story and the adversaries
那就是，如果我们在这个故事中是好人，而对手
are the bad people, you and I rather have to be perfect.
是坏人，那么你我必须完美无缺。
In the physical world, we have to lock every door, every window.
在现实世界中，我们必须锁上每一扇门、每一扇窗户。
Because if we mess up just one spot, the adversary can get in.
因为如果我们在某个地方犯了错误，对手就能进来。
And so where there's sort of this imbalance.
所以，这里就存在着某种不平衡。
The adversary just has to find the window that's
对手只需要找到开着的窗户
ajar to get into your physical home.
就可以进入你的房子。
The adversary just needs to find one user who's
对手只需要找到一个用户，他们
got a really bad password to somehow get into that system.
不知道怎么搞的，竟然用了一个非常烂的密码来尝试进入那个系统。
And so cybersecurity is hard.
所以网络安全很难。
And so what we'll see today really are techniques
所以我们今天会看到一些技巧，
that can let you create a gauntlet of defenses-- so not just one,
可以让你建立一道道防线，而不是只有一道防线，
but maybe two, maybe three.
而是两道，三道，甚至更多。
And even if the adversary gets in, another tenant of cybersecurity
即使对手突破了防线，网络安全的另一个原则
is at least, let's have mechanisms in place that detect
至少是，我们要建立机制来检测
the adversary, some kind of monitoring, automatic emails.
对手，一些监控机制，自动发送电子邮件。
You can increasingly see this already in the real world.
在现实生活中，你越来越能看到这些。
If you log into your Instagram account from a different city or state
如果你从不同的城市或州登录你的Instagram账户，
suddenly because maybe you're traveling, you
突然之间，可能是因为你在旅行，你
will-- if you've opted into settings like these-- often
会 - 如果你选择了这样的设置 - 经常
get a notification or an email saying, hey,
收到通知或电子邮件，说，嘿，
you seems to have logged in from Palo Alto rather than Cambridge.
你似乎是从帕洛阿尔托而不是剑桥登录的。
Is this, in fact, you?
这真的是你吗？
So even though we might not be able to keep the adversary out,
所以即使我们可能无法阻止对手进入，
let's at least minimize the window of opportunity or damage
至少我们要缩短对手可乘之机或减小其造成的损害
by letting humans like us know that something's been compromised.
通过让人类，像我们这样的人知道某些东西被入侵了。
Of course, there is a downside here.
当然，这里也有一些缺点。
And this is another theme of cybersecurity.
这也是网络安全的另一个主题。
Every time you improve something, you've got to pay a price.
每次你提升某样东西，你都要付出代价。
There's going to be a tradeoff.
会有权衡取舍。
And we've seen this with time and space and money and other such resources
我们已经看到，在设计系统时，时间、空间、金钱和其他资源方面都会有这种权衡取舍。
when it comes to designing systems already.
在设计系统方面，我们已经看到了。
What's the downside of this mechanism?
这种机制的缺点是什么？
Why is this perhaps a bad thing or what's the downside to you,
为什么这可能是一件坏事，或者对你来说，
the good person in the story?
这个故事中的好人来说，缺点是什么？
Yeah.
是的。
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
听众： [听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, if you've just forgotten your passcode,
大卫·马兰：是的，如果你只是忘记了密码，
it's going to be more difficult for you to log in.
你登录会更加困难。
Or maybe you just really need to get into your phone now
或者可能你真的需要马上进入你的手机，
and you don't really want to wait a minute.
你并不想等一分钟。
And if you, worse, if you keep trying, sometimes it'll
而如果你，更糟糕的是，如果你一直尝试，有时它会
change to two minutes, five minutes, one hour.
变成两分钟，五分钟，一个小时。
It'll increase exponentially.
它会呈指数级增长。
Why?
为什么？
Because Apple and Google figure that, they don't necessarily
因为苹果和谷歌认为，他们不一定
know what the right cutoff is.
知道正确的截止时间。
Maybe it's 10, maybe it's fewer, maybe it's more.
可能是10次，也可能是更少或更多。
But at some point, it is much more likely
但在某一点上，
that this is a hacker trying to get in than it is for getting your passcode.
这是一个黑客试图侵入的可能性远大于你忘记密码。
But in the corporate world, it can be even worse.
但在企业界，情况可能更糟糕。
There's a feature that lets phones essentially self-destruct whereby
有一个功能可以让手机自我毁灭，即
rather than just waiting you wait a minute,
而不是仅仅等待一分钟，
it will wipe the device, more dramatically.
它会更彻底地清除设备。
The presumption being that, no, no, no, no, no, if this is a corporate phone,
假设是，不，不，不，不，不，如果这是一部公司手机，
let's lock it down further so that it is an adversary,
让我们进一步锁定它，这样它就是一个对手，
the data is gone after 10 failed attempts.
如果连续 10 次尝试失败，数据就会消失。
But there's other mechanisms as well.
但也存在其他机制。
In addition to logging into phones via passcodes,
除了通过密码登录手机，
there's also websites like Gmail, for instance.
还有像 Gmail 这样的网站。
And it's very common, therefore, to log in to websites like these.
因此，登录这些网站非常常见。
And odds are, statistically, a lot of you
从统计学上讲，你们中很多人
are in the habit of reusing passwords.
有重复使用密码的习惯。
Like, no, don't nod if you are.
别点头，别点头。
We have cameras everywhere.
到处都是摄像头。
But maybe you're in the habit of reusing it.
但也许你习惯重复使用它。
Why?
为什么？
Because it's hard to remember really big long cryptic passwords.
因为很难记住那些又长又复杂又难懂的密码。
So mathematically, there's surely an advantage there.
所以从数学上讲，这样做肯定有优势。
Why?
为什么？
Because it just makes it so much harder, more time-consuming,
因为这使得入侵变得更加困难，更加耗时，
more risky for an adversary to get in.
对攻击者来说风险更大。
But the other tradeoff is like, my God, I just can't even
但是另一方面，天哪，我根本就记不住
remember most of my passwords as a result
大部分密码了，
unless I reuse the one good password I thought of and memorized already
除非我重复使用我之前想出的并记住的唯一一个好密码，
or maybe I write it down on a post-it note on my monitor,
或者我可能把它写在一张贴在显示器上的便利贴上，
as all too often happens in corporate workplaces.
这在企业工作场所太常见了。
Or maybe you're being clever and in your top right drawer,
或者你很聪明，在你的右上角抽屉里，
you've got a printout of all of your accounts.
你保存着所有账户的打印版。
Well, if you do, like ha-ha, so do a lot of other people.
好吧，如果你这样做了，哈哈，很多人也这样做。
Or maybe it's a little more secure than that,
或者可能比这安全一点，
but there are sociological side effects of these technological policies that
但是这些科技政策在社会层面上会产生一些副作用，
really until recent years were maybe underappreciated.
直到最近几年，这些副作用才被重视。
The academics, the IT administrators were mandating policies
学者、IT 管理员都在强制执行一些政策，
that you and I as human users were not necessarily behaving properly
而我们这些普通用户在面对这些政策时，并不一定能做出正确的行为。
in the face of.
面对。
So nowadays, there are things called password managers.
所以现在，有一些叫做密码管理器的工具。
And a password manager is just a piece of software on Macs,
密码管理器就是一个软件，它存在于 Mac 上，
on PCs, on phones that manage your passwords for you.
PC 上，手机上，它可以为你管理你的密码。
What this means specifically is when you go
具体来说，当你第一次
to a website for the very first time, you, the human,
访问一个网站时，你，作为人类，
don't need to choose your password anymore.
不再需要选择你的密码了。
You instead click a button or use some keyboard shortcut.
你只需要点击一个按钮或使用一些键盘快捷键。
And the software generates a really long cryptic password for you
软件会为你生成一个非常长、复杂、难以理解的密码，
that's not even eight characters.
甚至超过 8 个字符。
It might be 16 or 32 characters, can be even bigger than that, but with lots
它可能是 16 个字符，或者 32 个字符，甚至更多，并且包含大量的
of randomness.
随机性。
Definitely not going to be on that top 10 or that top 100 list.
这个密码肯定不会出现在前 10 名或前 100 名的列表中。
The software thereafter remembers that password
软件会记住那个密码
for you and even your username, whether it's your email address or something
以及你的用户名，无论它是你的电子邮件地址还是其他
else.
东西。
And it saves it onto your Mac or your phone or your PC's disk or hard drive.
它会将它保存到你的 Mac、手机、PC 的硬盘或磁盘上。
The next time you visit that same website, what you can do
下次你访问同一个网站时，你可以
is via menu or, better yet, a keyboard shortcut, log into the website
通过菜单，或者更好的是使用键盘快捷键，登录网站。
without even remembering or even knowing your password.
即使不记得或不知道你的密码。
I mean, to this day, I'll tell you, I don't even
我的意思是，直到今天，我会告诉你，我甚至
know anymore 99% of my own passwords.
不知道我自己 99% 的密码。
Rather, I rely on software like this to do the heavy lifting for me.
相反，我依赖这样的软件来为我完成繁重的工作。
But there's an obvious downside here, which
但这里有一个明显的缺点，就是
might be what if you're doing this?
如果你是这样做的，会怎样？
Yeah.
是的。
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众： [听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Right, so what if they find out the one password
大卫·马兰： 没错，所以如果他们找到了保护这个软件的密码，
that's protecting this software?
会怎样？
Because unstated by me up until now is that this password manager itself
因为我之前没有说明的是，这个密码管理器本身
has a primary password that protects all of those other eggs in the one basket,
有一个主密码，它保护着篮子里所有其他的鸡蛋，
so to speak.
可以这么说。
And my one primary password for my own password manager,
而我自己的密码管理器的唯一主密码，
it is really long and hard to guess.
它非常长而且很难猜。
And the odds that anyone's going to guess
任何人都能猜到的可能性
are just so low that I'm comfortable with that
实在是太低了，我对此感到很满意
being the one really difficult thing that I've committed to my memory.
这是我唯一需要记住的真正困难的东西。
But the problem is if someone does figure it out nonetheless somehow
但问题是，如果有人不管怎样还是能猜出来
or, worse, I forget what it is.
或者更糟糕的是，我忘记了它是什么。
Now, I've not lost access to one account, but all of my accounts.
现在，我不仅失去了一个帐户的访问权限，而且失去了所有帐户的访问权限。
Now, that might be too high of a price to pay.
现在，这可能是一个太高的代价。
But, again, if you're in the habit of choosing easy passwords like being
但是，同样，如果你习惯选择简单的密码，比如
on that top 10 list, reusing passwords, it's probably a net
出现在前 10 名列表中，重复使用密码，这可能是一个净
positive to incur this single risk versus the many risks you're
好处，因为承担了这种单一的风险，而不是你所承担的许多风险
incurring across the board with all of these other sites.
在所有这些其他网站上普遍存在的许多风险。
As for what you can use, increasingly our operating systems
至于你可以用什么，我们的操作系统越来越多地
come with support for this, be it in the Apple world, Google, Microsoft world,
支持这一点，无论是苹果世界、谷歌、微软世界，
or the like.
等等。
There's third party software you can pay for and download.
还有你可以付费下载的第三方软件。
But even then, I would beware.
但即使那样，我也要小心。
And I would ask friends whose opinion you trust or do
我会询问你信任的朋友，或者
some googling for reviews and the like.
在谷歌上搜索一些评论等等。
All too often in the software world have password managers
在软件世界里，密码管理器经常
been determined to be buggy themselves.
被发现本身就存在漏洞。
I mean, you've seen in weeks of CS50 how easy it is to introduce bugs.
我的意思是，在 CS50 的几周时间里，你已经看到了引入漏洞是多么容易。
And even the best of programmers still introduce bugs to software.
即使是最优秀的程序员也会在软件中引入漏洞。
So you're also trusting that the companies making this password
所以你也在信任制作这种密码的那些公司
management software is really good at it.
管理软件做得很好。
And that's not always the case.
而情况并非总是如此。
So beware there too.
所以也要小心。
But we'll also focus today on some of the fundamentals
但我们今天也将重点关注一些基础知识
that these companies can be using to better protect your data as well.
这些公司可以用来更好地保护你的数据。
But there's another mechanism, which odds are you're in the habit of using.
但还有一种机制，你可能习惯使用它。
Two-factor authentication, like most of us
双因素身份验证，就像我们大多数人
probably have to use this for some of your accounts--
可能不得不为你的某些帐户使用它，比如
your Harvard account, your Yale account, maybe your bank accounts, or the like.
你的哈佛账户、你的耶鲁账户，也许还有你的银行账户等等。
So what is two-factor authentication in a nutshell?
简而言之，什么是双重身份验证？
Yeah.
是的。
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, you get a second factor
戴维·马兰：是的，你会得到第二个因素
that you have to provide to the website or application
你需要向网站或应用程序提供它
to prove that it's you like a text to your phone
以证明你是你，比如发一条短信到你的手机上
or maybe it's an actual application that gets push notifications or the like.
或者可能是一个实际的应用程序，它会收到推送通知或类似的东西。
Maybe in the corporate world, it's actually
也许在企业界，它实际上是
a tiny little device with a screen on it that's on your keychain or the like.
一个带屏幕的小巧设备，挂在你的钥匙链上或者类似的地方。
Maybe it's actually a USB dongle that you have to plug into your work laptop.
也许它实际上是一个 USB 钥匙，你需要把它插到你的工作笔记本电脑上。
In short, it's some second factor.
简而言之，这是一个额外的因素。
And by factor, I mean something technical.
而“因素”的意思是指某种技术上的东西。
It's not just a second password, which would be one factor.
它不仅仅是第二个密码，因为密码只算一个因素。
It's a second fundamentally different factor.
它是第二个本质上不同的因素。
So generally speaking in the world of two-factor authentication or 2FA or MFA
所以在双重身份验证、2FA 或 MFA 的世界中，一般来说
is the generalization as multi-factor authentication,
多重身份验证是一个更通用的概念，
you have not just a password, which is something you know,
你不仅有一个密码，它是你知道的东西，
the second factor is usually something you have--
第二个因素通常是你拥有的东西——
whether it's your phone or that application or the keychain.
无论是你的手机、那个应用程序还是钥匙链。
It might also be biometrics like your fingerprints, your retinas,
它也可能是生物识别信息，比如你的指纹、你的视网膜，
or something else physically about you.
或者其他与你身体有关的东西。
But it's something that significantly decreases the probability
但它能显著降低一些攻击者
that some adversary is going to get into that account.
进入那个账号的可能性。
Why?
为什么？
Because right now, if you've only got a username and password,
因为现在，如果你只有用户名和密码，
your adversaries are literally every human in the world
你的攻击者实际上是世界上每一个人
with an internet connection, arguably.
都可以说是拥有网络连接的人。
But as soon as you introduce 2FA, now it's
但一旦你引入 2FA，现在就变成了
only people on campus or, more narrowly, only the people in Starbucks
只有校园里的人，或者更准确地说，只有星巴克里的人
at that moment who might physically have access
在那一刻可能会实际接触到
to your person and your second factor, in this case.
你的人和你第二个因素，在这种情况下。
More technically, what those technologies do is they send you
更准确地说，这些技术所做的就是向你发送
a one-time passcode, which is further secure because once it's used,
一个一次性密码，它更加安全，因为一旦使用，
there's hopefully some database that remembers that it has been used
希望有一些数据库会记住它已被使用
and cannot be used again.
并且不能再次使用。
So an adversary can't like sniff the airwaves and replay
因此，攻击者无法像嗅探无线电波一样重放
that passcode the next time they, indeed, expire,
这个密码，在下一次它过期时，他们确实会这样做，
which adds some additional defense.
这增加了一些额外的防御。
And you might type it into a phone or maybe a web app that
你可能把它输入到一个手机上，或者是一个看起来像这样的网页应用程序。
looks a little something like this.
看起来有点像这样。
So passwords thus far, some defenses, therefore, any questions on this
所以到目前为止，密码有一些防御，因此，对这种机制有任何问题吗？
here mechanism?
这里机制？
No?
没有？
All right, well, let's consider this.
好吧，让我们考虑一下。
Odds are, with some frequency, you forget these passwords, especially
很可能你会经常忘记这些密码，尤其是在
if you're not using a password manager.
你不使用密码管理器的情况下。
And so you go to Gmail and you actually have
所以你会去 Gmail，并且实际上有
to click a link like this, Forgot Password.
要点击像这样的链接，忘记密码。
And then it typically emails you to initiate
然后它通常会向你发送电子邮件，以启动
a process of resetting that password.
重置密码的过程。
But if you can recall, has anyone ever clicked a link like that
但是如果你还记得，有没有人点击过这样的链接
and then got an email with your password in the email?
然后收到了包含你密码的电子邮件？
Maybe if you ever see this in the wild, that
也许如果你在现实生活中看到过这种情况，那么
is to say in the real world, that is horrible, horrible design.
也就是说，在现实世界中，这是非常糟糕的设计。
Why?
为什么？
Because well-designed websites, not unlike CS50 Finance,
因为设计良好的网站，就像 CS50 Finance 一样，
which had a users table, should not be storing username-- rather,
它有一个用户表，不应该存储用户名，而是
should not be storing passwords in the clear, as it actually is.
不应该明文存储密码，而实际上它就是这么做的。
It should somehow be obfuscated so that even
它应该以某种方式被混淆，即使
if your database from CS50 Finance or Google's database
如果你来自 CS50 Finance 或 Google 的数据库
is hacked and compromised and sold on the web,
被黑客入侵并被盗，然后在网上出售，
it should not be as simple as doing like select star
它不应该像执行 select star 一样简单
from Account semicolon to see what your actual passwords are.
from Account 分号来查看你的实际密码。
And the mechanism that well-designed websites use
而设计良好的网站使用的机制
is actually a primitive back from like week 5 when we
实际上是我们在第 5 周的时候学过的原始方法
talked about hashing and hash tables.
谈到了哈希和哈希表。
This time, we're using it for slightly different purposes.
这一次，我们将它用于略微不同的目的。
So in the world of passwords, on the server side, there's often a database
所以在密码的世界里，在服务器端，通常会有一个数据库
or maybe, more simply, a text file somewhere on the server
或者更简单地说，服务器上的某个地方有一个文本文件
that just associates usernames with passwords.
它只是将用户名与密码关联起来。
So to keep things simple, if there's at least two users like Alice and Bob,
为了简单起见，如果至少有两个用户，比如 Alice 和 Bob，
Alice's password is maybe apple.
Alice 的密码可能是 apple。
Bob's password is maybe banana, just to keep the mnemonics kind of simple.
Bob 的密码可能是 banana，只是为了让记忆助记符更简单一些。
If though that were the case on the server
如果在服务器上是这种情况
and that server is compromised, whoever the hacker now
并且服务器被入侵了，现在黑客
has access to every username and every password, which in and of itself
可以访问每个用户名和每个密码，这本身
might not be a huge deal because maybe the server administrators can just
可能不是什么大不了的事，因为服务器管理员可以
disable all of the accounts, make everyone change their password,
禁用所有帐户，让每个人都更改他们的密码，
and move on.
然后继续。
But there's also this attack known as password stuffing, which
但还有另一种攻击被称为密码填充，它
is a weirdly technical term, which means when you compromise one database,
是一个奇怪的技术术语，意思是当你入侵一个数据库时，
you know what?
你知道吗？
Take advantage of the naivety of a lot of us users.
利用我们很多用户的单纯。
Try the compromised Apple password, the banana
尝试被入侵的 Apple 密码，香蕉
password not on the compromised website, but other websites
密码不在被入侵的网站上，而是在其他网站上
that you and I might have access to, the presumption
你我可能可以访问的，假设
being that some of us in this room are using
是，我们中有些人正在使用
the same passwords in multiple places.
相同的密码在多个地方。
So it's bad if your password is compromised on one server
所以如果你的密码在一台服务器上被入侵
because, by transitivity, so can all of your other accounts be compromised.
因为，通过传递性，你的其他所有帐户也可能会被入侵。
So in the world of hashing, this was the picture
所以在哈希的世界里，这就是我们
we drew some time ago, we can apply this same logic whereby, mathematically,
很久以前画的图，我们可以应用相同的逻辑，即在数学上，
a hash function is like some function F and the input is X
哈希函数就像一个函数 F，输入是 X
and the output or the range is F of X. That
输出或范围是 F(X)。这
was sort of the fancy way of describing mathematically
用数学术语来描述的一种方式
hashing as a process weeks ago.
几周前我们谈到的哈希算法
But here, at a simpler level, the input to this process
但在这里，更简单的来说，这个过程的输入
is going to be your actual password.
将会是你的真实密码
The output is going to be a hash value, which in week 5
输出将会是一个哈希值，在第五周的时候
was something simple generally like a number--
一般是一个简单的数字
1 or 2 or 3 based on the first letter.
根据第一个字母是 1、2 或者 3
That's not going to be quite as naive an approach as we
这不会像我们在
take in the password world.
密码世界中那样简单
It's going to look a little more cryptic.
它会看起来更加隐晦
So Apple weeks ago might have just been 1, banana might have been 3.
所以几周前，苹果可能是 1，香蕉可能是 3
But now let me propose that in the world of real world system design, what
但是现在我想说，在真实世界系统设计的领域中，数据库人员应该存储的
the database people should actually store
实际上不是苹果
is not apple, but rather this cryptic value.
而是这个隐晦的值
And you can think of this as sort of random, but it's not random.
你可以把它看作是一种随机值，但它不是随机的
Because it is the result of an algorithm, some mathematical function
因为它是一个算法的结果，一个数学函数的结果
that someone implemented and smart people evaluated and said,
有人实现了这个算法，聪明的人们对其进行了评估，然后说
yes, this seems to be secure, secure in the sense
是的，这个算法看起来很安全，安全的意义在于
that this hash function is meant to be one way.
这个哈希函数是一个单向函数
So this is not encryption, a la Caesar Cipher from weeks
所以这不是加密，不像几周前我们学习的凯撒密码
ago whereby you could just add 1 to encrypt and subtract 1 to decrypt.
你可以通过加 1 来加密，减 1 来解密
This is one way in the sense that given this value,
它是单向的，也就是说，给定一个值
it should be pretty much impossible mathematically to reverse the process
从数学上来说，逆向操作基本是不可能的
and figure out that the user's password was originally apple.
并推断出用户的密码最初是苹果
Meanwhile banana, back in week 5 for simplicity, for hashing into a table,
同时，香蕉，为了简便，在第五周的时候，我们将其哈希到一个表中
we might have had a simple output of 2, since B
我们可能会得到一个简单的输出值 2，因为 B
is the second letter of the English alphabet.
是英文字母表中的第二个字母
But now the hash value of banana, thanks to a fancier mathematical function,
但是现在，由于一个更复杂的数学函数，香蕉的哈希值
is actually going to be something more cryptic like this.
实际上会是一个更加隐晦的值，就像这样
And so what the server really does is store not apple and banana, but rather
因此，服务器实际存储的不是苹果和香蕉，而是
those two seemingly cryptic values.
这两个看起来很隐晦的值
And then when the human, be it Alice or Bob,
然后，当人类用户，无论是爱丽丝还是鲍勃
logs in to a web form with their actual username and password, like Alice,
登录到网页表单中并输入他们的真实用户名和密码，比如爱丽丝，苹果，鲍勃，香蕉，网站
apple, Bob, banana, the website no longer even
甚至不再知道爱丽丝的密码是苹果，鲍勃的密码是香蕉
knows that Alice's password is apple and that Bob's is banana.
但是没关系
But that's OK.
因为只要服务器使用相同的代码
Because so long as the server uses the same code
与注册帐户时使用的代码一致
as it was using when these folks registered for accounts,
爱丽丝可以输入苹果，点击回车，通过 HTTP 发送到服务器
Alice can type in apple, hit Enter, send it via HTTP to the server.
服务器可以使用相同的哈希函数对 A-P-P-L-E 进行操作
The server can run that same hash function on A-P-P-L-E.
如果值匹配，服务器就可以得出结论，很有可能，是的
And if the value matches, it can conclude with high probability, yes,
这就是最初的爱丽丝，或者说，这就是最初的鲍勃
this is in fact, the original Alice or this, in fact, is the original Bob.
所以服务器从不保存密码，但它会使用相同的哈希函数
So the server never saves the password, but it does use the same hash function
反复比较那些相同的哈希值，无论何时这些用户登录
to compare those same hash values again and again whenever these folks log in
again and again.
一遍又一遍。
So, in reality, here's a simple one-way hash for both Alice's
所以，实际上，这是爱丽丝和鲍勃密码的简单单向散列。
and Bob's passwords in the real world.
以及鲍勃在现实世界中的密码。
It's even longer, this is to say, than what I
它甚至更长，也就是说，比我之前用过的更短的例子还要长。
used as shorter examples a moment ago.
用过的更短的例子还要长。
But there is a corner case here.
但是这里有一个极端情况。
Suppose that an adversary is smart and has some free time
假设一个攻击者很聪明，并且有一些空闲时间
and isn't necessarily interested in getting into someone's account
并且不一定有兴趣进入别人的账户
right now, but wants to do a bit of prework
现在，但想做一些预先的工作
to decrease the future cost of getting into someone's account.
以降低将来进入别人的账户的成本。
There is a technical term known as a rainbow table,
有一个专业术语叫彩虹表，
which is essentially like a dictionary in the Python sense or the SQL sense,
它本质上就像 Python 意义上的字典或 SQL 意义上的字典，
whereby in advance an adversary could just try hashing all of the fruits
这样，攻击者就可以提前尝试对世界上所有的水果进行散列运算
of the world or, really, all of the English words of the world or, rather,
或者说，世界上所有的英语单词，或者说，
all possible four-digit, four-character, eight-character passcodes in advance
所有可能的四位数、四字符、八字符密码，
and just store them in two columns--
并把它们存储在两列中——
the password, like 0000 or apple or banana,
密码，比如 0000 或 apple 或 banana，
and then just store in advance the hash values.
然后预先存储散列值。
So the adversary could effectively reverse engineer the hash
因此，攻击者可以有效地逆向工程散列
by just looking at a hash, comparing it against its massive database of hashes,
只需查看散列值，将其与庞大的散列值数据库进行比较，
and figuring out what password originally correspond to that.
并找出最初与之对应的密码。
Why then is this still relatively safe?
为什么这仍然相对安全？
Rainbow tables are concerning.
彩虹表令人担忧。
But they don't defeat passwords altogether.
但它们并不能完全击败密码。
Why might that be?
为什么呢？
Yeah.
是的。
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: OK, so the adversary might not
大卫·马兰：好的，所以攻击者可能不会
know exactly what hash function the company is using.
知道公司使用的散列函数的具体类型。
Generally speaking, you would not want to necessarily keep that private.
一般来说，你不会想把这个保密。
That would be considered security through obscurity.
这将被视为通过模糊来保证安全。
And all it takes is like one bad actor to tell the adversary what
只需要一个坏人告诉攻击者使用的是什么
hash function is being used.
散列函数。
And then that would put your security more at risk.
那样会使你的安全面临更大的风险。
So generally in the security world, openness
因此，在安全领域，公开性
when it comes to the algorithms in process
在算法方面
is generally considered best practice.
通常被认为是最佳实践。
And the reality is, there's a few popular hash functions out there
现实是，有一些流行的散列函数
that any company should be using.
任何公司都应该使用。
And so it's not really keeping a secret anyway.
所以，它实际上并没有保密。
But other thoughts?
还有其他想法吗？
Why is this rainbow table not such a concern?
为什么这个彩虹表不是那么令人担忧？
AUDIENCE: It takes a lot longer for the [INAUDIBLE]..
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: It takes a lot longer for the adversary
大卫·马兰：攻击者需要更长时间
to access that information because this table could get long.
来访问这些信息，因为这个表可能会很长。
And even more along those lines-- anyone want to push a little harder?
还有更多类似的观点——有人想更深入地探讨一下吗？
This doesn't necessarily put all of our passwords at risk.
这并不一定会使我们所有的密码面临风险。
It easily puts our four-digit passcodes at risk.
这很容易使我们的四位数密码面临风险。
Why?
为什么？
Because this table, this dictionary would have, what, 10,000 rows?
因为这个表，这个字典会有，什么，一万行？
And we've seen that you can search that kind of like that
我们已经看到你可以这样搜索
or even regenerate all of the possible values.
甚至可以重新生成所有可能的值。
But once you get to eight-character passcodes,
但是一旦你使用八个字符的密码，
I said it was 4 quadrillion possibilities.
我说过有 4 千万亿种可能性。
That's a crazy big dictionary in Python or crazy big list
在 Python 中，这是一个非常大的字典，或者是一个非常大的列表
of some sort in Python.
某种形式的 Python。
That's just way more RAM or memory than a typical adversary is going to have.
这远远超出了典型对手所能拥有的 RAM 或内存。
Now, maybe if it's a particularly resourced adversary like a government,
现在，也许如果是一个资源特别丰富的对手，比如政府，
a state more generally, maybe they do have supercomputers
更一般地说，一个国家，也许他们确实拥有超级计算机
that can fit that much information.
可以容纳如此多的信息。
But, fine, then use a 16-character passcode
但是，好吧，那就使用 16 个字符的密码
and make it an unpronounceable long search space
并使其成为一个不可发音的巨大搜索空间
that's way bigger than 4 quadrillion.
比 4 千万亿还要大。
So it's a threat, but only if you're on that horrible top 10 list or top 100
所以这是一种威胁，但只有当你在我们之前讨论过的可怕的排名前 10 名或排名前 100 名的列表中时才会出现。
or short passcode list that we've discussed thus far.
或者短密码列表。
So here's though a related threat that's just worth knowing about.
所以这里有一个相关的威胁，值得了解一下。
What's problematic here?
这里的问题是什么？
If we introduce two more users, Carol and Charlie,
如果我们再添加两个用户，卡罗尔和查理，
and just for the semantics of it, whose password happened to be cherry.
为了语义的完整性，他们的密码恰好是 cherry。
What if they both happened to have the same password and this database
如果他们恰好使用相同的密码，而这个数据库
is compromised?
被泄露了？
Some hacker gets in.
一些黑客入侵了。
And just to be clear, we wouldn't be storing apple, banana, cherry, cherry.
需要明确的是，我们不会存储 apple、banana、cherry、cherry。
We'd still be storing, according to this story, these hashes.
根据这个故事，我们仍然会存储这些哈希值。
But why is this still concerning?
但为什么这仍然令人担忧？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众： [听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
大卫·马兰：没错。
If you figure out just one of them, now you've got the other.
如果你只找到了其中一个，那么你就得到了另一个。
And this is, in some sense, just leaking information, right?
从某种意义上说，这只是泄露信息，对吧？
I don't maybe at a glance what I could do with this information.
我可能无法一眼看出我能用这些信息做什么。
But if Carol and Charlie have the same password, you know what?
但如果卡罗尔和查理使用相同的密码，你知道吗？
I bet they have the same password on other systems as well.
我敢打赌他们在其他系统上也使用相同的密码。
You're leaking information that just does no good for anyone.
你泄露的信息对任何人都没有好处。
So how can we avoid that?
那么如何避免这种情况呢？
Well, we probably don't want to force Carol or Charlie to change
好吧，我们可能不想强迫卡罗尔或查理更改
their password, especially when they're registering.
他们的密码，尤其是在注册的时候。
You definitely don't want to say, sorry, someone's already using that password,
你绝对不想说，抱歉，有人已经在使用那个密码了，
you can't use it as well.
你也不能使用它。
Because that too would leak information.
因为这也会泄露信息。
But there's this technique in computing known as salting
但是，在计算中有一种叫做加盐的技术
whereby we can do this instead.
我们可以这样做。
If cherry we in this scheme hashes to a value like this, you know what?
如果 cherry 在这个方案中哈希到这样的值，你知道吗？
Let's go ahead and sprinkle a little bit of salt into the process.
让我们在过程中加点盐。
And it's sort of a metaphorical salt whereby this hash function now takes
这是一种比喻性的盐，在这个哈希函数现在需要的地方
two inputs, not just the password, but some other value known as a salt.
两个输入，不仅仅是密码，还有另一个被称为“盐”的值。
And the salt can be generally something super short like two characters even,
而且这个“盐”通常非常短，甚至只有两个字符，
or something longer.
或者更长。
And the idea is that this salt, much like a recipe,
而这个“盐”的作用，就像食谱一样，
should of perturb the output a little bit,
应该会稍微扰乱输出，
make it taste a little bit differently, if you will.
换句话说，让它尝起来稍微有点不同。
And so concretely, if we take the word cherry and then when Carol registers,
具体来说，如果我们以“cherry”这个词为例，然后当 Carol 注册时，
for instance, we randomly choose a salt of 50, 5-0, so two characters,
例如，我们随机选择一个“盐”为 50，5-0，也就是两个字符，
the hash value now-- because there's two inputs--
现在的哈希值（因为有两个输入）
might now be this value.
可能是这个值。
But if for Charlie, we still have cherry, but we change the 50,
但如果对于 Charlie 来说，我们仍然使用“cherry”，但将 50 更改为
we might see this instead.
我们可能会看到这个值。
Notice that for this first example, Carol, 50,
注意第一个例子，Carol，50，
the salt is preserved in the hash value, just so you know what it was
“盐”被保存在哈希值中，这样你就知道它是什么了
and you can sprinkle the same amount of salt, so to speak, next time.
下次你可以撒同样的盐量，打个比方。
But that's the whole hash value for Carol in this case.
但这是这种情况下的 Carol 的整个哈希值。
But if Charlie also has a password of cherry, but we change the salt to,
但如果 Charlie 的密码也是“cherry”，但我们将“盐”更改为，
say, 49 arbitrarily, that whole hash value changed.
比如随意地改为 49，整个哈希值就变了。
And so now in my hash database, I'm going to see different salts there,
因此，现在在我的哈希数据库中，我将看到不同的“盐”，
different values, which is going to effectively cover up the fact
不同的值，这将有效地掩盖了
that Carol and Charlie have the same password.
Carol 和 Charlie 使用相同的密码的事实。
Now, if we have so many users that we run out of salts,
现在，如果我们的用户数量太多，以至于“盐”不够了，
that still might leak some information.
这仍然可能泄露一些信息。
But that's kind of a we can kick down the road and probabilistically not
但这可以先放到一边，从概率上来说，
going to happen if you require passwords of sufficiently long length, most
如果你的密码长度足够长，这种情况很可能不会发生，大多数
likely.
可能性。
So any questions on salting, which to be clear,
所以关于加盐，说清楚一点，
is just a mechanism for decreasing the probability
这只是一个减少概率的机制，
that an adversary is going to glean information
让攻击者获取信息的概率
that you might not want them to have?
是你可能不希望他们拥有的信息？
So what does this mean concretely?
那么，这具体意味着什么？
When you get an email from a website saying "click this link
当你收到一个网站的电子邮件，上面说“点击此链接
to reset your password," it's not the website, if well designed,
重置你的密码”，如果网站设计良好，
is being difficult or shy and not telling you your password,
并不是网站故意为难你，或者不好意思告诉你你的密码，
the web administrators just do not know, ideally, your password.
理想情况下，网站管理员根本不知道你的密码。
So what are they doing?
那么他们到底在做什么？
They're probably sending you a link, similar in spirit
他们可能正在发送一个链接，与之类似
to a one-time password, there's some random unique string in there
是那种一次性密码，链接中包含一个随机的唯一字符串
that's unique to you.
这个字符串只属于你。
They've stored that in their database.
他们已经将这个字符串存储在他们的数据库中。
So as soon as you click on that link, they check their database
所以，当你点击这个链接时，他们会检查他们的数据库
and be like, oh, wait a minute, I know I set this link a minute ago to David.
然后说，“哦，等等，我记得一分钟前给 David 设置了这个链接。”
Let me just trust now-- because probabilistically there's no way
现在就相信他吧，因为从概率上来说，不可能
someone guessed this URL within 60 seconds--
有人能在 60 秒内猜到这个 URL
let's trust that whatever he wants to type in as his new password
相信他想要输入的任何新密码都是他想要的。
should be associated with that Malan account in the database.
应该与数据库中的 Malan 帐户相关联。
But if, conversely, you ever get an email saying your password is 123456
但是，相反地，如果你收到一封电子邮件，说你的密码是 123456
or whatever it is, it is clearly not being hashed, let alone salted,
或者无论是什么，它显然没有被哈希，更不用说加盐了，
on the server.
在服务器上。
And that is not a website to do anything particularly sensitive with.
而且这不是一个用来处理任何特别敏感信息的网站。
All right, so what more can we do?
好的，那我们还能做什么呢？
Well, let's pick up where we left off in week two on the art of cryptography,
好吧，让我们从第二周的密码学艺术中继续学习，
this art, the science of scrambling information, but in a reversible way.
这种艺术，信息混乱的科学，但它是一种可逆的方式。
So whereas hashing, as we've described it here, is really tends to be one-way,
所以，正如我们在这里描述的那样，哈希实际上往往是单向的，
whereby you should not be able to reverse the process unless you cheat
除非你作弊，否则你不应该能够逆转这个过程
and make a massive table of all of the inputs
并创建一个包含所有输入的大型表格
and all of the outputs, which isn't really so much
以及所有输出，这实际上并不算
reversing as it is just looking it up.
逆转，而只是查找它。
Cryptography, like in week 2, can actually
密码学，就像第二周一样，实际上
be a solution to a lot of problems, not just sending messages
可以解决很多问题，而不仅仅是发送消息
across a crowded room.
穿过拥挤的房间。
We, weeks ago, really focused on this type of cryptography
几周前，我们确实专注于这种类型的密码学
whereby you've got some plain text message.
你得到了一些纯文本消息。
You've got a key, like a secret number 1 or 13 or something else.
你有一个密钥，比如一个秘密数字 1 或 13 或者其他什么。
The cipher, which might be a rotational cipher or a substitution cipher,
密码，它可能是一个循环密码或一个替换密码，
some algorithm, and then ciphertext was the term
一些算法，然后密文是术语
of art for describing the scrambled version.
用于描述混淆版本的艺术。
That should look like random zeros and ones or letters
它应该看起来像随机的零和一或字母
of the alphabet or the like.
的字母或类似的东西。
This though was reversible, whereby you could just
然而，它是可逆的，你可以只
input the ciphertext with the key and get back out the plain text.
输入密文和密钥，然后获取纯文本。
Maybe you have to change a positive number to a negative number.
也许你必须将一个正数改为负数。
But the key is really the same.
但密钥实际上是一样的。
Be it plus 1 minus 1 or plus 13 minus 13, the process was symmetric.
无论是加 1 减 1 还是加 13 减 13，该过程都是对称的。
And, indeed, what we talked about in week two
而且，事实上，我们在第二周讨论的是
was an example of something called secret key cryptography, where
一个被称为密钥密码学的示例，其中
there's, indeed, one secret between two parties, a.k.a.
确实，在双方之间只有一个秘密，也就是
symmetric cryptography.
对称密码学。
Because encryption is pretty much the same as decryption, but maybe
因为加密和解密几乎相同，但也许
you change the sign on the key itself.
你改变了密钥本身的符号。
But this is not necessarily all we want.
但这不是我们想要的一切。
Because here's that general process.
因为这是那个一般过程。
Here's the letter A. Here's the key of 1.
这是字母 A。这是密钥 1。
We outputed in week 2 a value of B. That's not necessarily
我们在第二周输出了一个 B 值。那不一定是
the solution to all of our problems.
所有问题的解决方案。
Why?
为什么？
Well, if two people want to communicate securely, they need some shared secret.
嗯，如果两个人想安全地沟通，他们需要一些共享的秘密。
So, for instance, if I wanted to send a secret message to Rongxin
所以，例如，如果我想给荣鑫发送一个秘密信息
in the back of the room here, he and I have better
在房间的后面，我和他最好
agreed upon a secret in advance.
提前商定一个秘密。
Otherwise, how can I possibly send a message, encrypt it in a way
否则，我怎么才能发送消息，以一种方式加密它呢
that he can reverse?
他可以逆转吗？
I mean, I could be like, (WHISPERING) let's use a key of 1.
我的意思是，我可以像这样（小声说）让我们使用一个键1。
(SPEAKING NORMALLY) But obviously, anyone in the middle
（正常说话）但很明显，任何在中间的人
has just now heard that.
刚刚听到了这一点。
So we might as well not communicate securely at all.
所以我们也可能根本就不安全地交流。
So there's this kind of chicken-and-the-egg problem,
所以这是一种鸡和蛋的问题，
not just contrived here in lecture.
不只是在讲座中编造的。
But the first time I want to buy something on amazon.com
但当我第一次想在亚马逊网站上买东西的时候
with my credit card, I would like my credit card to be encrypted,
用我的信用卡，我希望我的信用卡被加密，
scrambled somehow.
以某种方式被加密。
But I don't know anyone personally at amazon.com, let alone someone
但我并不认识亚马逊网站上的任何人，更不用说一个人
that I've prearranged some secret for my Mac and their servers.
我已经为我的 Mac 和他们的服务器预先安排了一些秘密。
So it seems that we fundamentally can't use symmetric cryptography
所以看来我们基本上不能一直使用对称加密
all of the time, unless we have some other mechanism for securely generating
所有的时间，除非我们有一些其他机制来安全地生成
that key, which we don't have as the common case in the world today.
这个密钥，但我们今天在世界上没有作为通用的情况。
Thankfully, mathematicians years ago came up
值得庆幸的是，多年的数学家想出了
with something known as asymmetric cryptography, which
一种被称为非对称加密的东西，它
does not require that you use the same secret in both directions.
不需要你在两个方向使用相同的秘密。
This is otherwise known as public key cryptography.
这也被称为公钥密码学。
And it works essentially as follows.
它的工作原理如下。
When you want to take some plaintext message and encrypt it,
当你想要获取一些明文信息并对其进行加密时，
you use the recipient's public key.
你使用收件人的公钥。
So if Rongxin is my colleague in back and he has a public key,
所以如果 Rongxin 是我后面的同事，他有公钥，
it is public by definition.
它根据定义是公开的。
He can literally shout for the whole room
他实际上可以大声喊叫，让整个房间
to hear what his public key is, which effectively is just
听到他的公钥是什么，它实际上只是一个
some big, seemingly random number.
一些大的，看似随机的数字。
But there's some mathematical significance of it.
但它有一些数学意义。
And I can write that down.
我可以把它写下来。
Heck, you can all write it down if you too want to send him secure messages.
哎呀，如果你也想要给他发送安全消息，你们都可以把它写下来。
And out of those two inputs, we get one output, the ciphertext,
从这两个输入中，我们得到一个输出，密文，
that I can then hand off to people in the room in those virtual envelopes.
然后我可以把它交给房间里的人，放在那些虚拟信封里。
And it doesn't matter if all of you have heard his public key.
而且你们是否都听到了他的公钥并不重要。
Because you can perhaps guess where this is going.
因为你可能已经猜到这将要去哪里了。
How would Rongxin reverse this process?
Rongxin 如何逆转这个过程？
He's not going to use one public key.
他不会使用一个公钥。
He's going to use, not surprisingly, a corresponding private key.
不出所料，他会使用一个相应的私钥。
And so in asymmetric cryptography or public key cryptography,
因此，在非对称加密或公钥加密中，
you really have a key pair, a public key and a private key.
你实际上有一对密钥，一个公钥和一个私钥。
And for our mathematical purposes today, let
为了我们今天的数学目的，让我们
me just stipulate that there's some fancy math involved, such
我规定这里涉及一些高级数学，例如
that when you choose that key or, really, those keys,
当你选择那个密钥，或者说，那些密钥时，
there's a mathematical relationship between them.
它们之间存在数学关系。
And knowing one does not really give you any information about the other.
知道其中一个并不会真正给你关于另一个的信息。
Why?
为什么？
Because these numbers are so darn big it would take adversaries more
因为这些数字非常大，它需要对手更多的时间来
time than we all have on Earth to figure out via brute force
我们所有人在地球上都没有时间通过蛮力来找出
what the corresponding private key is.
对应的私钥是什么。
The math is that good.
数学就是这么好。
And even as computers get faster, we just
即使计算机的速度越来越快，我们也
keep using bigger and bigger keys, more and more bits
继续使用越来越大的密钥，越来越多的位
to make the math even harder for adversaries.
让对手的数学运算变得更加困难。
So when Rongxin receives that message, he uses his private key,
因此，当荣鑫收到该消息时，他使用他的私钥，
takes the ciphertext I sent him through the room,
将我通过房间发送给他的密文
and gets back out the plaintext.
并获得明文。
So this is exactly how HTTPS works effectively
因此，这正是 HTTPS 有效工作的方式
to securely establish a channel between me and Amazon.com, gmail.com.
以安全地建立我与 Amazon.com、gmail.com 之间的通道。
Any website starting with https:// uses public key cryptography to come up
任何以 https:// 开头的网站都使用公钥密码学来
with, initially, a secret.
最初，有一个秘密。
And in practice, it turns out, mathematically,
在实践中，结果表明，从数学上来说，
it's faster to use secret key crypto.
使用秘密密钥加密更快。
So very often, people will use asymmetric crypto
因此，人们经常使用非对称加密
to generate a big shared key and then use the faster algorithms thereafter.
生成一个大的共享密钥，然后使用更快的算法。
But it does solve asymmetric cryptography,
但这确实解决了非对称密码学，
that chicken-and-the-egg problem, by giving us all public keys and private
那个先有鸡还是先有蛋的问题，通过为我们提供所有公钥和私钥
keys.
密钥。
If you've heard of RSA, Diffie-Hellman, elliptic curve cryptography,
如果你听说过 RSA、Diffie-Hellman、椭圆曲线密码学，
there's different algorithms for this that you can actually
有不同的算法，你可以实际
study in higher level, more theoretical classes.
在更高级别、更理论的课程中学习。
But there's a bunch of different ways mathematically to solve this problem.
但是有很多不同的数学方法可以解决这个问题。
But those are the primitives involved.
但这些是所涉及的原语。
And how many of you have heard of now passkeys, which
你们中有多少人听说过现在的密码钥匙，它
is kind of only just catching on in recent months, literally.
实际上，只是在最近几个月才流行起来。
If I had to make any prediction this semester,
如果我必须对这学期做出任何预测，
odds are, you're going to see these in more and more places.
很可能，你会在越来越多的场所看到它们。
And in fact, the next time you register for a website or log into a website,
事实上，下次你注册或登录网站时，
look for a link, a button that maybe doesn't say passkeys, per se.
寻找一个链接，一个按钮，它可能并不一定叫“密码钥匙”。
It's often called passwordless login.
它通常被称为无密码登录。
But it's really referring to the same thing.
但它实际上指的是同一件事。
Passkeys are essentially a newish feature of operating systems,
密码钥匙本质上是操作系统的一个比较新的功能，
be it Mac OS or Windows or Linux or the OS running on your phone,
无论是 Mac OS、Windows、Linux 还是手机上运行的操作系统，
that doesn't require that you choose a username and password anymore.
都不再要求你选择用户名和密码。
Rather, when you visit a website for the very first time,
相反，当你第一次访问一个网站时，
your device will generate a public and private key pair.
你的设备会生成一对公钥和私钥。
Your device will then send to the website for what
然后，你的设备会向网站发送你的
you're registering your public key so that it has one of the values,
你注册的公钥，以便它具有其中一个值，
but you keep your private key, indeed, private.
但你保持你的私钥，确实，是私密的。
And using the same mathematical process that I alluded to earlier,
使用我之前提到的相同数学过程，
you can therefore log into that website in the future
因此，你可以在将来登录到那个网站
by proving mathematically that you are, in fact, the owner
通过数学证明你实际上是
of the corresponding private key.
对应的私钥的所有者。
So, in essence, if we use a picture like this,
因此，本质上，如果我们使用这样的图片，
when you proceed to log in to that website again-- and, again,
当你再次登录到该网站时，再次，
that website has stored your public key--
该网站已存储您的公钥。
it essentially uses something known as digital signatures--
它本质上使用的是一种叫做数字签名的东西。
you're familiar with this term, you've heard it in the wild--
你熟悉这个词，你曾在生活中听到过它。
whereby the website will send you a challenge message,
通过这种方式，网站会向你发送一条挑战信息，
like some random number or string of text.
就像一些随机数字或文本字符串。
It's just some random value.
这只是一个随机值。
If you then effectively encrypt it with your private key or run both of those
如果你用你的私钥对其进行加密，或者将这两个值都
through a particular algorithm, you'll get back a signature.
通过特定的算法运行，你将得到一个签名。
And that signature can be verified by the website by using your public key.
然后，该网站可以使用您的公钥来验证该签名。
So digital signatures are kind of an application of cryptography
因此，数字签名是对密码学的应用
but in the reverse direction.
但方向相反。
In the world of encryption, you use someone's public key
在加密领域，你使用某人的公钥
to send a message encrypted.
来发送一条加密的消息。
And they use their private key to decrypt it.
他们用自己的私钥解密它。
In the world of signatures, or really passkeys,
在签名领域，或者更确切地说是通行密钥，
you reverse the process, whereby you use your private key to effectively encrypt
你反转这个过程，用你的私钥对
some random challenge you've been sent.
发送给你的随机挑战进行加密。
And the website, the third party, can use your public key
然后，网站这个第三方可以使用你的公钥
to verify, OK, mathematically, that response came from David.
来验证，好的，从数学上讲，这个响应来自于大卫。
Because I have his public key on file.
因为我保存了他的公钥。
So what's the upside of this?
那么，这样做有什么好处呢？
We just get out of the business of passwords and password managers
我们只需要摆脱密码和密码管理器的困扰
more generally.
更广泛地说。
You do have to trust and protect your devices, be it
你确实需要信任并保护你的设备，无论是
your phone or your laptop or desktop all the more.
你的手机、笔记本电脑还是台式电脑，都要更加注意。
And that's going to open another possible threat.
这将带来另一种可能的威胁。
But this is a way to chip away at what is becoming the reality
但这是消除正逐渐成为现实的东西的一种方式
that you and I probably have dozens, hundreds of usernames and passwords
你和我都可能有几十个，甚至几百个用户名和密码
that's probably not sustainable long-term.
这在长期内可能无法持续。
And, indeed, we read to often about hacks in the wild as a result.
而且，我们经常看到，由于这种原因，黑客攻击在现实中很常见。
Questions then on cryptography or passkeys?
那么，关于密码学或通行密钥的问题吗？
All right, just a few more building blocks to equip you for the real world
好的，再讲几个构建模块，让你在现实世界中运用。
before we sort of maybe do a final check for understanding of sorts.
在我们进行最后的理解检查之前。
So when it comes to encryption, we can solve other problems as well.
因此，说到加密，我们还可以解决其他问题。
And in this too is a feature you should increasingly be seeking out.
这也是你应该越来越多的去寻找的一个功能。
So end-to-end encryption refers to a stronger use of encryption
端到端加密指的是更强大的加密方式
than most websites are actually in the habit of using.
比大多数网站使用的加密方式更强。
Case in point, if you're using HTTPS to send an email to Gmail,
举个例子，如果你用 HTTPS 向 Gmail 发送电子邮件，
that's good because no one between you and Gmail servers
这是好事，因为在你和 Gmail 服务器之间
presumably can see the message because it's encrypted.
没有人可以查看这条消息，因为它被加密了。
It just looks like random zeros and ones.
它看起来就像随机的 0 和 1。
So it's effectively secure from people on the internet.
所以它实际上是安全的，免受互联网上的人们的攻击。
The emails are not secure from like nosy employees at Google
这些邮件并不能保护 Google 的那些爱管闲事的工作人员。
who do have access to those servers.
谁有权访问这些服务器。
Now, maybe through corporate policy, they shouldn't or physically don't.
现在，也许是出于公司政策，他们不应该或者实际上也不能。
But, theoretically, there's someone at Google
但理论上，谷歌里有人
who could look at all of your email if they were so inclined.
如果他们想的话，可以查看你的所有电子邮件。
Hopefully it's just not a long list of people.
希望这只是一个不长的名单。
But end-to-end encryption ensures that if you're
但端到端加密确保的是，如果你
sending a message from A to B, even if it's going through C in the middle--
从A发到B的信息，即使它经过了中间的C——
be it Google or Microsoft or someone else-- end-to-end encryption
无论是谷歌、微软还是其他人——端到端加密
means that you're encrypting it between A and B. And so even C in the middle
意味着你是在A和B之间加密的。因此，即使是中间的C
has no idea what's going on.
也不知道发生了什么事。
This is not true of services like Gmail or Outlook.
像Gmail或Outlook这样的服务就不是这样。
This is true of services like iMessage or WhatsApp
像iMessage或WhatsApp这样的服务才是这样。
or Signal or Telegram or other services where if you poke around, also
或者Signal或Telegram或其他服务，如果你仔细研究，你也会看到
you'll see literally mention of end-to-end encryption.
真正提到端到端加密。
It's a feature that's becoming a little more commonplace,
这正成为越来越普遍的功能，
but something you should seek out when you don't necessarily trust or want
但当你并不信任或不想信任
to trust the machine in the middle, the point
信任中间的机器时，这一点
C between A and B. So, indeed, when sending messages on phones
A和B之间的C。所以，确实，在手机上发送消息时
and even video conferencing nowadays too.
甚至如今的视频会议也是这样。
And here's something where sometimes you kind of have to dig.
而这里有一些你可能需要仔细研究的东西。
Most of us are familiar with Zoom certainly by now.
我们大多数人现在肯定都熟悉Zoom了。
And if we go into Zoom settings, which I did
如果我们进入Zoom设置，我今天早上就
this morning to take this screenshot, this is what it looks like as of now.
早上做了这件事来截取这张截图，这就是现在的样子。
Here's the menu of options for creating a new meeting.
这是创建新会议的选项菜单。
And toward the bottom here-- it's a little small--
这里面靠近底部——有点小——
you'll notice that you have two options for encryption.
你会注意到有两个加密选项。
And funny, enough the one that's typically selected
有趣的是，通常选择
by default, unless you opt in to the other one, is enhanced encryption.
默认的是增强加密，除非你选择另一个。
Brilliant marketing, right?
很棒的营销，对吧？
Who doesn't want enhanced encryption.
谁不想要增强加密呢。
It is weaker than this encryption though, which is end-to-end encryption.
不过它比这种加密更弱，这种加密是端到端加密。
End-to-end encryption means that when you're
端到端加密意味着当你
having a video conference with one or more people,
与一个人或多个人进行视频会议时，
not even Zoom can see or hear what you're talking about.
甚至Zoom也无法看到或听到你在说什么。
Enhanced encryption means no one between you
增强加密意味着你与Zoom之间
and Zoom can hear or see what you're talking about.
的任何人无法听到或看到你在说什么。
So end-to-end ensures that it's A to B, and if Zoom is C In the story,
所以端到端确保它是从A到B，如果Zoom是故事中的C，
even Zoom can't see what you're doing.
即使Zoom也无法看到你在做什么。
Now, there are some downsides.
现在，有一些缺点。
And there's some little fine print here.
这里有一些小字。
When you enable end-to-end encryption on a cloud-based service like Zoom,
当你启用像Zoom这样的云服务上的端到端加密时，
you can't use cloud recordings anymore.
你将无法再使用云录制。
Why?
为什么？
Well, if Zoom by definition mathematically
好吧，如果根据定义，Zoom在数学上
can't see or hear your meeting, how are they going to record it for you?
无法看到或听到你的会议，他们将如何为你录制？
It's just random zeros and ones.
它只是一些随机的 0 和 1。
You can still record it locally on your Mac or PC,
你仍然可以在你的 Mac 或 PC 上本地录制，
but end-to-end encryption ensures that you
但是端到端加密确保你
don't have to worry about prying eyes-- be it a company, be it a government,
不必担心窥探的目光——无论是公司、政府，
a state more generally.
还是更广泛地说，一个国家。
And so societally, you'll start to see this discussed probably even
因此，在社会上，你可能会看到人们讨论这个问题，甚至
more than it already is when it comes to personal liberties and freedom
比现在讨论的还要多，因为这涉及到个人自由
among citizens of countries and states because
在国家和地区的公民中，因为
of the implications for actual privacy that these primitives
这些基本原理对实际隐私的影响
that we've been discussing and that you even explored in week 2,
我们一直在讨论的，甚至你在第二周也探索了，
albeit weakly, with these ciphers we used in the real world.
尽管很弱，但我们使用了这些在现实世界中使用的密码。
But encryption has one other use that's worth knowing about too and yet
但是加密还有另一个值得了解的用途，并且
another feature to turn on.
还有另一个功能可以开启。
So when it comes to deleting files, odds are, most everyone in the room
所以，说到删除文件，很可能，房间里的每个人
knows on a Mac or PC that when you drag a file to the trashcan or the recycle
都知道在 Mac 或 PC 上，当你将文件拖到垃圾桶或回收站时
bin, it doesn't actually go away unless you right click
里，它实际上并不会消失，除非你右键单击
or Control click or go to the appropriate menu and empty the trash.
或者按 Ctrl 键单击或转到相应的菜单并清空垃圾桶。
But did anyone know that even when you empty the trash or recycle bin,
但是有没有人知道，即使你清空了垃圾桶或回收站，
the file also doesn't really go away.
文件实际上并没有消失。
Your operating system typically just forgets where it is.
你的操作系统通常只是忘记了它的位置。
But the zeros and ones that compose the file or files you tried to delete
但是构成你试图删除的文件的那些 0 和 1
are still there for the pickings, especially
仍然在那里，可以随时取用，尤其是
if someone gets physical or virtual access to your system.
如果有人获得了你的系统的物理或虚拟访问权限。
So, for instance, here is a whole bunch of ones and zeros.
例如，这里有一堆 1 和 0。
Maybe it's representing something on my hard drive.
也许它代表着我硬盘上的某些东西。
And suppose that I want to go ahead and delete
假设我想继续删除
a file that comprises these zeros and ones, these bits here.
一个包含这些 0 和 1 的文件，这些位在这里。
Well, when your operating system deletes the file,
那么，当你的操作系统删除文件时，
even if you click on Empty Trash or Empty Recycle Bin,
即使你点击清空垃圾桶或清空回收站，
it essentially just forgets about those bits, but doesn't actually change them.
它实际上只是忘记了那些位，但并没有真正改变它们。
Only once you create a new file or download something else
只有当你创建新文件或下载其他东西时
do some of those zeros and ones end up getting overwritten.
其中一些 0 和 1 最终会被覆盖。
And per the yellow remnants here, the implication of this contrived example
根据这里黄色的残留部分，这个人为例子意味着
is that even at this point in time you can still recover
即使在此时此刻，你仍然可以恢复
like half of the file, it would seem.
似乎有大约一半的文件。
So maybe the juicy part with a credit card number
所以也许包含信用卡号码的那部分
or a message that you really wanted to delete or the like, there's
或者你真的很想删除的邮件之类的，这里仍然
still remnants on the computer's hard drive here.
存在着电脑硬盘上的残留信息。
So what's the alternative?
那么，有什么替代方法吗？
Well, if you really want to be thorough, you
好吧，如果你真的想要彻底，你可以
could delete files and then download the biggest possible movies you
删除文件，然后下载你能找到的最大电影，
can to really fill up your hard drive.
来真正填满你的硬盘。
Because, probabilistically, you would end up
因为，从概率上来说，你最终会
overwriting all of those zeros and ones eventually.
最终覆盖掉所有这些 0 和 1。
But that's not really a tenable solution.
但这并不是一个可行的解决方案。
It would just take too much time and it's
这将花费太多时间，而且
fraught with possible simple mistakes.
充满了可能出现的简单错误。
So what should we do instead, well, maybe we
那么我们应该怎么做呢？也许我们应该
should securely delete information.
安全地删除信息。
And securely delete would mean when you actually
安全删除意味着当你真正
empty the recycle bin or the trash can, what happens to the original zeros
清空回收站或垃圾桶时，原始的 0 和 1 会发生什么
and ones is that you take them and you change all of them
和 1 呢？你会将它们全部更改
to zeros or all of them to ones or all of them to random zeros and ones.
为 0，或者全部更改为 1，或者全部更改为随机的 0 和 1。
Why?
为什么？
So that you can still reuse those bits now,
这样你就可以继续使用那些比特了，
but there's no remnants even on the computer's hard drive
但是，即使是在电脑的硬盘驱动器上，也不会有残留
that they were once there.
表明它们曾经存在。
But even now, this is not fully robust.
但是即使现在，这也不是完全可靠的。
Why?
为什么？
It turns out that because of today's electronics and solid state devices,
事实证明，由于当今的电子产品和固态器件，
there might still be remnants of files on them because these hard drives,
这些硬盘驱动器上可能仍然存在文件的残留，因为这些硬盘驱动器，
these storage devices nowadays are smart enough
如今的存储设备足够智能，
that if they realize that parts of them are failing,
如果它们意识到自己的一部分正在失效，
they might prevent you from changing data in certain corners.
它们可能会阻止你更改某些角落的数据。
So if you think of your memory as like a big rectangle, some of the bits
因此，如果你将你的内存想象成一个大矩形，其中一些比特
might get blocked off to you just over time.
可能会随着时间的推移而被屏蔽。
So there might still be remnants there.
所以那里可能仍然存在残留。
So if you really are worried about a sibling, an employer, or a government
所以，如果你真的担心你的兄弟姐妹、你的雇主或政府
like finding data on that system, there might actually still be remnants.
会找到那个系统上的数据，实际上可能仍然存在残留。
Now, you can go extreme and just physically
现在，你可以走极端，直接物理
destroy the device, which should be pretty effective.
销毁设备，这应该是非常有效的。
But that's going to get pretty expensive over time when you want to delete data.
但随着时间的推移，当你想要删除数据时，这将会非常昂贵。
Or, again, we can use encryption as the solution to this problem.
或者，我们还可以使用加密来解决这个问题。
So, again, encryption is increasingly in the real world
所以，加密在现实世界中越来越重要
an amazing tool for your toolkit because it can be deployed in different ways.
成为你的工具箱中一个很棒的工具，因为它可以以不同的方式部署。
So, in this case, full disk encryption is something
所以，在这种情况下，全盘加密是你可以
you can enable in Windows or Mac OS.
在 Windows 或 Mac OS 上启用的功能。
Nowadays, it's typically enabled by default on iOS
如今，它通常默认在 iOS 上启用
and you can opt in as well on other platforms.
你也可以在其他平台上选择加入。
In the world of full disk encryption, instead of storing any of your files
在全盘加密的世界中，你不会将任何文件
as a plain text, like in their original raw format,
以纯文本形式存储，比如以原始格式存储，
you essentially randomize everything on the disk instead.
而是将磁盘上的所有内容随机化。
You rely on the user's password or some unique string
你会依赖用户的密码或他们知道的某个唯一字符串
that they know when you log into your Mac or PC
当你登录你的 Mac 或 PC 时
to essentially scramble the entire contents of the hard drive.
来对硬盘驱动器上的所有内容进行加扰。
And it's not quite as simple as that.
而且它并不像看起来那样简单。
Typically, there's a much larger key that's
通常，有一个更大的密钥被
used that in turn is protected by your actual password.
使用，而这个密钥又由你的实际密码保护。
But, in this case, this means that if someone steals your laptop while you're
但，在这种情况下，这意味着如果你在
not paying attention in Starbucks or the airport or even your dorm room,
即使你在星巴克、机场或甚至宿舍里没有注意，
even if they open the lid and don't have your password,
即使他们打开了盖子，而且没有你的密码，
they're not going to be able to access any of the data
他们也无法访问任何数据，
because it's just going to look like zeros and ones.
因为它们看起来只是一堆零和一。
Even if they remove the hard drive from your device,
即使他们将硬盘从你的设备上拆除，
plug it into another device, they're only going to see zeros and ones.
插入另一台设备，他们也只会看到零和一。
Now, if you walk away from your laptop at Starbucks with the lid open
现在，如果你在星巴克离开你的笔记本电脑，而且盖子是开着的
and you're logged in, there is a window of opportunity.
而你又登录了，那么就会出现一个可乘之机。
Because the data has got to be decrypted when you care about it and when
因为当你关心数据并且正在使用它时，数据必须被解密。
you're using it.
你正在使用它。
So here too is another example of best practice.
所以这里也是另一个最佳实践的例子。
You should minimally be closing the lid of your laptop,
你至少应该关上笔记本的盖子，
making sure it's logging you out or at least locking the screen,
确保你已退出登录，或者至少锁定屏幕，
so that someone can't just walk off with your device
这样，别人就不能直接拿走你的设备
and have access to your logged in account.
并访问你已登录的账户。
But full disk encryption essentially decreases the probability
但是，全盘加密实际上降低了
that an adversary is going to be successful.
对手成功的概率。
In the world of Macs, it's called FileVault.
在Mac的世界里，它被称为FileVault。
It's in your System Preferences.
它在你的系统偏好设置中。
Windows, it's called BitLocker.
在Windows中，它被称为BitLocker。
There's third party solutions too.
也有一些第三方解决方案。
Here too, we have to trust that Microsoft and Apple don't
同样，我们必须相信微软和苹果不会
screw up and write buggy code.
搞砸并写出有错误的代码。
But generally speaking, turning on features like these things
但总的来说，打开这些功能
are good for you.
对你来说是好的。
Except what's maybe an obvious downside of doing this?
除了可能有一个明显的缺点？
What's that?
是什么呢？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众： [听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, if you forget your password.
大卫·马兰：没错，如果你忘记了密码。
There's no mathematician in the world who
世界上没有哪个数学家
is probably going to be able to recover your data for you.
可能能够帮你恢复你的数据。
So there too, it's maybe a hefty tradeoff.
所以，这也是一个不小的取舍。
But hopefully you have enough defenses in place,
但希望你已经有了足够的防御措施，
be it your-- a good password, a password manager,
无论是你的——一个好的密码，一个密码管理器，
maybe even printing out your primary password on a sheet of paper,
甚至可能将你的主密码打印在一张纸上，
but locking it in a box or bringing it home so that no one near you
但是把它锁在盒子里或者带回家，这样你周围的人
actually has physical access, you can at least mitigate some of these risks.
实际上都没有物理访问权限，你至少可以减轻一些这些风险。
You'll read about, though, in the real world even this,
不过，你会读到，在现实世界中，即使是这种，
which is like an adversarial use of full disk encryption.
这就像是一种对抗性的全盘加密使用方式。
Sometimes when hackers get into systems, this
有时，当黑客侵入系统时，这种情况
has happened literally with hospital systems, municipal government systems,
实际上发生在医院系统、市政政府系统，
and the like.
等等。
If they hack into them, they don't just delete the data or just create havoc,
如果他们入侵了它们，他们不会仅仅删除数据，也不会仅仅制造混乱，
they will proactively encrypt the server's hard drive
他们会主动地用某种只有黑客知道的随机密钥加密服务器的硬盘
with some random key that only the hacker knows.
用某种只有黑客知道的随机密钥加密服务器的硬盘。
They will then demand that the hospital or the town
然后，他们会要求医院或城镇
pay them, often in Bitcoin or some cryptocurrency
向他们支付赎金，通常是比特币或某种加密货币
to decrease the probability of being caught,
为了降低被抓住的可能性，
and they'll only turn over that key to decrypt the data if someone actually
他们只会将该密钥交出来解密数据，如果有人真的
pays up.
付了钱。
So here too, there's sort of a dark side of these mathematical principles.
所以这里也有这些数学原理的阴暗面。
So there too, it's always a trade off between good people and perhaps bad.
所以，这里也永远是好人与坏人之间的权衡。
Well, maybe before we wrap and before we serve
好吧，也许在我们结束之前，在我们准备
some cake in the transept, Carter, can you join me one last time?
在过道里上蛋糕之前，卡特，你能最后一次加入我吗？
But, first, before I turn things over to me and Carter, here's your problem
但首先，在我把事情交给我和卡特之前，这是你的问题
set 10, a sort of unofficial homework.
集 10，一种非官方的家庭作业。
One, among your takeaways for today, you should
第一，在今天你应该学习到的东西中，你应该
start using a password manager or even these fancier passkeys, at least
开始使用密码管理器，甚至这些更高级的密码，至少
for your most sensitive accounts.
用于您最敏感的账户。
So anything medical, financial, particularly personal,
所以任何医疗，金融，尤其是个人，
like this is a very concrete takeaway and action item.
就像这是一个非常具体的要点和行动项目。
I wouldn't sit down and try to change all of your accounts over.
我不会坐下来尝试更改所有账户。
Because knowing humans, You're not going to get through the whole to-do list.
因为了解人类，你不可能完成所有待办事项。
So maybe do it the next time you log into that account,
所以也许下次登录该账户时，
turn on some of these features or add it to a password manager
启用一些这些功能或将其添加到密码管理器中
or at least start with the most important.
或者至少从最重要的开始。
Two, turning on two-factor authentication
第二，启用双重身份验证
beyond where you have to at places like Harvard and Yale,
除了像哈佛和耶鲁这样的地方必须这样做之外，
but certainly bank accounts, privates, anything medical, personal,
但当然包括银行账户、私人信息、任何医疗、个人信息，
or the like.
等等。
And then lastly, where you can, turning on end-to-end encryption.
最后，在您能够的情况下，启用端到端加密。
Being careful with it, you don't want to go
小心使用，你不想
and during lecture, hopefully no one clicked the turn on FileVault button
在课堂上，希望没有人点击了启用 FileVault 按钮
while we're in class.
在我们上课的时候。
Because closing your laptop lid while things are being encrypted
因为在加密过程中关闭笔记本电脑盖子
is generally bad practice.
通常是不好的做法。
See us after though if you did do that a moment ago.
如果你刚才做了，之后来找我们。
So here's just then three actionable takeaways.
所以，这里只有三个可行的要点。
But we thought we'd conclude by taking a few final minutes for a CS50 quiz
但我们想用几分钟时间来做一个 CS50 小测验来总结
show of sorts, a final check for understanding using some questions
算是展示，用一些问题来最后检查理解
we come up with ourselves, but also some of the review questions
我们自己想出来的，但也包括一些复习问题
that you all kindly contributed as part of the most recent problem set.
你们都在最近的习题集中贡献了这些问题。
So some of these questions come from you yourselves.
所以，其中一些问题来自你们自己。
And let me go ahead and turn things over to Carter here to help run the show.
让我把事情交给卡特来帮助主持。
We will invite you at this point to take out that same device
现在，我们邀请您拿出同一台设备
as you had earlier.
就像您之前一样。
This is the same URL as before.
这是和之前一样的网址。
But if you closed the tab, you can reopen it here.
但如果您关闭了标签页，您可以在此处重新打开它。
To make things a little fun-- because we still have some cookies
为了让事情更有趣一点，因为我们还有
left-- could we get three final CS50 volunteers?
一些饼干，我们可以再请三位 CS50 志愿者吗？
OK, one hand is already up.
好的，已经有一只手举起来了。
How about two hands there?
那两双手怎么样？
And how about three hands?
三个人来玩怎么样？
Over here.
这边！
All right, yes, sure, a round of applause for our final volunteers.
好的，没错，当然，让我们为最后的志愿者鼓掌！
Come on up.
上来吧！
[APPLAUSE]
[掌声]
On the line are some delicious Oreo cookies.
奖品是一些美味的奥利奥饼干。
If the three of you would like to come over and take
如果你们三个想过来，
any of these seats in the middle, you will be our human players,
坐在中间的任何一个座位上，你们就是我们的真人玩家，
but we'll invite everyone in the group to play too.
但我们也会邀请小组里的每个人一起玩。
Do you want to take a mic and introduce yourself to the world?
你们想拿个麦克风，向全世界介绍一下自己吗？
AUDIENCE: Sure.
观众：当然。
Hi, I'm Dani.
嗨，我叫丹尼。
I'm a first year in WIG C. And I'm planning on studying economics.
我是 WIG C 的一年级生，我计划学习经济学。
DAVID MALAN: Nice, welcome.
大卫·马兰：很好，欢迎。
AUDIENCE: Hi, I'm Rochelle.
观众：嗨，我叫罗谢尔。
I'm from the best state, Ohio.
我来自最好的州，俄亥俄州。
DAVID MALAN: [INAUDIBLE]
大卫·马兰：[听不清]
AUDIENCE: And I'm a freshman in Greeno.
观众：我是一名格林诺的新生。
I'm planning on concentrating in CS.
我计划主修计算机科学。
DAVID MALAN: Nice, welcome.
大卫·马兰：很好，欢迎。
And?
还有呢？
AUDIENCE: My name is Jackson.
观众：我叫杰克逊。
I'm from Indiana.
我来自印第安纳州。
I live in Thayer.
我住在塞耶。
I'm a first year.
我是一年级生。
And I'm studying linguistics and Germanic languages and literatures.
我正在学习语言学和日耳曼语言及文学。
DAVID MALAN: Welcome as well.
大卫·马兰：也欢迎你。
So, if our volunteers could have a seat, you're
所以，如果我们的志愿者可以坐下来，你们
going to want to be able to see this screen or that one.
会想要能够看到这个屏幕或那个屏幕。
So you can move your chairs if you would like.
所以，你们可以随意移动椅子。
Carter is going to kindly cue up the software, which hopefully everyone
卡特将好心地启动软件，希望每个人
has on their phones as well.
的手机上也都安装了。
And I should have mentioned, do you have your phone with you?
我应该提到，你手机带了吗？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Do you have your phone with you?
大卫·马兰：你手机带了吗？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: OK, do you have your phone over there?
大卫·马兰：好的，你在那边有手机吗？
OK, what's your name again?
好的，你叫什么名字来着？
AUDIENCE: Rochelle.
观众：罗谢尔。
DAVID MALAN: OK, Rochelle will be right back,
大卫·马兰：好的，罗谢尔马上就回来，
if you want to go grab your phones.
如果你想拿手机的话。
And in the meantime, we're going to go ahead and-- thank
在此期间，我们将会继续——感谢
you so much-- we're going to go ahead and cue up the screens here
你们，我们会继续启动这些屏幕
for the CS50 quiz show.
用于 CS50 知识问答节目。
It's about 20 questions in total, the first few of which
总共大约 20 道题，前几道题
are going to focus on cybersecurity to see how well we
将集中在网络安全方面，看看我们
can check our current understanding.
对当前的理解掌握得如何。
The rest will be questions written by you in the days leading up to today.
其余的都是你们在今天之前几天写的题。
All right, Carter, let's go ahead and reveal the first question.
好的，卡特，让我们继续揭晓第一个问题。
And note that you can win up to 1,000 points this time per question.
注意，这次每道题最多可以获得 1000 分。
It's not just about being right or wrong.
这不仅仅是关于对错。
And you get more points the faster you buzz in as well.
而且你按铃越快，获得的积分就越多。
So we'll see who's on the top based on all of the guest user names.
所以我们会根据所有客人的用户名来查看谁排在第一位。
All right, here we go, Carter, question one,
好了，我们开始了，卡特，第一个问题，
what is the best way to create a password?
创建密码的最佳方法是什么？
Substitute letters with numbers or punctuation signs,
用数字或标点符号替换字母，
ensure it's at least eight characters long,
确保密码至少有八个字符，
have a password manager generated for you,
使用密码管理器为你生成一个密码，
or include both lowercase and uppercase letters?
还是包含大小写字母？
All right, let's see what the results are.
好的，让我们看看结果。
Almost everyone said have a password manager generate it for you.
几乎每个人都说使用密码管理器为你生成一个密码。
90% of you said that's the case.
你们中有 90% 的人说这是真的。
And, indeed, that one is correct.
实际上，那个答案是正确的。
Nicely done.
做得好。
Let's go ahead and see the random usernames you've chosen.
让我们看看你们选择的随机用户名。
So this looks like it's web_hexidecimalidentifier to keep
所以这看起来像是 web_hexidecimalidentifier 来保持
things anonymous.
匿名。
So if you are OAF9E, nicely done, but there's
所以如果你叫 OAF9E，做得好，但是
a whole lot of ties up at the top.
在排行榜上有很多并列第一名。
All right, and I see-- well, just to keep things interesting,
好的，我看到...为了保持有趣，
you had 792 points.
你获得了 792 分。
You had--
你获得了...
AUDIENCE: 917.
观众：917 分。
DAVID MALAN: 917 points, 917 points.
戴维·马兰：917 分，917 分。
So it's a close race here.
所以这现在是一场激烈的比赛。
Number two, what is a downside of two-factor authentication?
第二题，双因素身份验证有什么缺点？
You might lose access to the second factor.
你可能会失去对第二个验证因素的访问权限。
Your account becomes too secure.
你的账户变得太安全了。
You can be notified someone else is trying to access your account.
你会收到通知，告知其他人试图访问你的账户。
You can pick any authentication you like.
你可以选择你喜欢的任何身份验证方式。
Hopefully, you can reload.
希望你能重新加载。
You might have missed that one.
你可能错过了那个。
And the number one answer was might lose access to the second factor.
第一个答案是可能失去对第二个验证因素的访问权限。
Indeed, 93% of you got that.
实际上，你们中有 93% 的人答对了。
And we're up to 1,375 points, 792 points, and--
现在分数是 1375 分，792 分，还有...
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: OK, and forced reload.
戴维·马兰：好的，强制重新加载。
So, yes, you tried reloading the page and hopefully it'll click back in.
所以，是的，你尝试重新加载页面，希望它能重新点击。
All right, Carter, number 3.
好的，卡特，第三题。
We have, what would you see if you tried to read an encrypted disk?
我们有，如果你试图读取一个加密的磁盘，你会看到什么？
You would see a random sequence of zeros and ones,
你会看到一系列随机的 0 和 1，
scrambled words from the user's documents,
用户文档中的乱码，
all of the user's information, or all one's?
用户的所有信息，还是所有 1？
About 10 seconds remain.
还剩大约 10 秒钟。
Is it working for you now?
你现在能使用了吗？
OK.
好的。
All right, three seconds.
好的，还剩三秒钟。
And the ranked answers are a random sequence of zeros and ones.
排名第一的答案是随机序列的 0 和 1。
91% of you indeed got that right.
你们中有 91% 的人确实答对了。
Let's see who's winning on the guest screen.
让我们看看在访客屏幕上谁赢了。
Web user a28c3, nicely done.
网页用户 a28c3，做得好。
But it's still a close tie among three of you anonymous participants.
但你们三个匿名参与者仍然处于胶着状态。
Number four, which type of encryption is most secure--
第四题，哪种加密方式最安全？
enhanced encryption, end-to-end encryption, full scale encryption,
增强型加密、端到端加密、全方位加密、
advanced encryption?
高级加密？
About five seconds.
大约五秒钟。
And most popular response is the correct one, end-to-end encryption
最受欢迎的答案也是正确的，端到端加密
with 92% of you.
你们的正确率为 92%。
Nice.
不错。
We're up to 2,375, 3,792, and 2,917.
你们的得分分别是 2375，3792 和 2917。
And good job to these three folks in the front of our list.
恭喜榜单前三名。
All right, Carter, number 5, the last on cybersecurity.
好的，卡特，第五题，最后一个关于网络安全的题目。
When would it make sense to store your password on a sticky note
什么时候把你的密码写在便签上
by your computer?
放在电脑旁边？
When it's too complicated to remember, when
当它太复杂记不住的时候，当
you need to access your account quickly, when you share your account with family
你需要快速访问你的账户的时候，当你与家人共享账户的时候
members, never.
成员，永远不要。
Oh.
哦。
And the most popular response was never, which is indeed correct.
最受欢迎的答案是永远不要，这确实是正确的。
And only 79% of you think that right now.
只有 79% 的人现在这样认为。
It is never OK to store it on a post-it note on your computer.
永远不要将它储存在电脑上的便签上。
You should minimally be using today's password manager for that same process.
至少应该使用今天的密码管理器来执行相同的操作。
All right, two of you, a28c3 and c9a23 are still atop the list.
好的，你们两个人，a28c3 和 c9a23 仍然位列榜首。
We have 3,000-plus points, 3,000-plus points,
你们的得分都超过 3000 分，
and probably about the same as well.
可能也差不多。
All right, now we move on to the user-generated content
好的，现在我们进入用户生成的內容
that you all from Harvard and Yale generated for us.
你们所有来自哈佛和耶鲁大学的同学为我们生成的内容。
Number 6, what is the variable type that stores true/false values?
第六题，存储真值/假值的值类型是什么？
Boolean, string, integer, or double?
布尔值、字符串、整数或双精度？
About 10 seconds to come up with this.
大约 10 秒钟想出来。
We saw these in different languages, these types.
我们在不同的语言中看到了这些类型。
But the idea was the same.
但概念是一样的。
And in two seconds, we'll see that the answer
两秒钟后，我们会看到答案
is Boolean with 96% response rate.
是布尔值，正确率为 96%。
All right, what else do we have here?
好的，我们还有其他问题吗？
It's still a two-way tie at the top.
榜首仍然是并列第一。
All right, next question, Carter, is number 7.
好的，卡特，下一题是第七题。
What placeholder would you use when trying
在尝试打印 C 语言中的浮点数时，你会使用什么占位符？
to print a float in C, a float in C?
在 C 语言中打印浮点数，在 C 语言中打印浮点数？
Seven seconds.
七秒钟。
I'll defer to the visual syntax on the screen for this one.
这个问题我将参考屏幕上的视觉语法。
And the most popular and correct answer is, indeed, %f.
最受欢迎的答案也是正确的，确实是 %f。
We never saw %fl and we definitely didn't see %float.
我们没有见过 %fl，我们当然也没有见过 %float。
Two of you, though, are still in the lead.
不过，你们两个人仍然处于领先位置。
Nicely done, whoever you are.
干得漂亮，无论你是谁。
All right, next question, what does I++ do in C++ where I is an integer value?
好的，下一题，在 C++ 中，当 I 是一个整数值时，I++ 会做什么？
Note, for the record, we did not teach C++ in this course,
注意，为了记录，我们在这门课中没有教 C++，
but this question is from you.
但这个问题是你们提出的。
I will admit it's the same as in C, which we did teach.
我承认它与 C 语言中的一样，我们教过 C 语言。
Decrements the integer, deletes the integer, increments the integer by one,
递减整数，删除整数，将整数加 1，
or reassigns the integer to zero?
或者将整数重新分配为零？
The most popular answer and correct answer
最受欢迎的答案也是正确答案
is increments the integer by one.
是将整数加一。
It definitely doesn't decrement, so.
它肯定不会递减，所以。
All right, two responses still atop the list.
好的，两个回复仍然位于列表的首位。
And here we have 6,000-plus, 6,000, and 6,000.
这里有 6000 多个、6000 个和 6000 个。
So it's getting closer.
所以越来越接近了。
Using a hash table to retrieve data is useful
使用哈希表检索数据很有用
because it theoretically achieves a search time of O of n, O of n log n,
因为它理论上可以实现 O(n)、O(n log n) 的搜索时间，
O of log n, or O of 1?
O(log n) 还是 O(1)？
Five seconds to make your decision.
还有 5 秒钟做出决定。
Getting a little harder.
越来越难了。
And let's see the results.
让我们看看结果。
O of 1, only 30% of you got the correct answer from a very core week 5 topic.
O(1)，只有 30% 的人从第 5 周的核心主题中得到了正确答案。
That is the theoretical hope of a hash table.
这就是哈希表的理论希望。
In practice, though, to be fair, it can devolve, as we saw, into O of n.
不过，公平地说，在实践中，它可能会退化为 O(n)，正如我们所见。
We didn't really see those other two answers in the context of hash tables
我们并没有真正看到其他两个答案在哈希表的上下文中
specifically.
具体而言。
All right, wow, a28c3 is in the lead now.
好的，哇，a28c3 现在领先了。
Let's take a look at number 10, halfway there.
让我们看看第 10 题，已经过半了。
What is the first program we made in CS50?
我们在 CS50 中编写的第一个程序是什么？
This should be fast.
这应该很快。
All right, Greet, Meow, DNA, Hello, world?
好的，Greet、Meow、DNA、Hello, world？
One second.
一秒钟。
And it was, indeed, Hello, world, Hello, world.
确实，是 Hello, world，Hello, world。
All right, still in the lead with 10,000 points.
好的，仍然领先，得分 10000 分。
And now let's move on to the second half.
现在让我们进入下半场。
Question 11, when malloc is used to allocate memory in a C program,
第 11 题，当在 C 程序中使用 malloc 分配内存时，
that memory is allocated in the pile, heap, bin, or stack?
该内存是在堆、堆栈、箱子还是堆栈中分配的？
Very creative set of answers.
非常有创意的一组答案。
Five seconds.
还有 5 秒钟。
All right, and the results have heap at 43%.
好的，结果显示堆为 43%。
Malloc was from the heap at the top.
Malloc 是从顶部的堆分配的。
The stack is where function calls go.
堆栈是函数调用发生的地方。
It's getting a little more worrisome here.
这里有点令人担忧了。
But that's OK.
但没关系。
Still in the lead with perfect score, it seems, 11,000 points.
看来仍然领先，分数为 11000 分。
Next up is number 12.
接下来是第 12 题。
Which data structure allows you to change its size dynamically and store
哪种数据结构允许您动态更改其大小并存储
values in different areas of the memory--
不同区域的内存中的值——
an array, a queue, a linked list, or a stack?
数组、队列、链表还是堆栈？
Change its size dynamically and store different values
动态更改其大小并存储不同的值
in different areas of the memory.
在内存的不同区域中。
And the answer from the group is a linked list at 62%, which is correct.
小组的答案是链表，占 62%，这是正确的。
An array, as we defined it, cannot be resized.
数组，按照我们的定义，不能调整大小。
You can create a new array, copy everything over.
您可以创建一个新的数组，将所有内容复制到新数组中。
I'm starting to think maybe we shouldn't end the class on this note.
我开始觉得也许我们不应该以这种方式结束课程。
But that's OK.
但没关系。
We'll move on.
我们继续吧。
12,000 points for the lead.
领先者获得 12000 分。
And number 13, what does CSS stand for in web development--
第13题，在网页开发中，CSS代表什么？
computer style sheets, cascading style sheets, creative style systems,
计算机样式表，层叠样式表，创意样式系统，
colorful sheets styles?
多彩的样式表？
And most popular answer is correct with 81%, cascading style sheets.
最受欢迎的答案是正确的，81%的人选择了层叠样式表。
On the top 10 list here at 1,300 points, still a perfect score,
在排行榜上，得分1300，仍然是满分，
and our three human volunteers are doing well here too.
我们的三位人类志愿者也表现出色。
14, how to represent a decimal number 5 in binary.
第14题，如何用二进制表示十进制数字5。
All right, here we go.
好的，我们开始吧。
I'll let you read these.
我来读一下这些选项。
All rights, fingers crossed, decimal number 5 in binary is, indeed, 101.
好了，祈祷一下，二进制的十进制数字5确实是101。
Because that's a 4 plus 0 plus 1 gives us a decimal 5.
因为4加0加1等于十进制的5。
All right, next question, and amazing a28c3, whoever you are out there,
好的，下一个问题，a28c3，你是谁，
nicely done.
做得很好。
Who is the CS50 mascot--
CS50的吉祥物是谁？
cat, duck, robot dog Spot, Oscar the Grouch?
猫，鸭子，机器人狗Spot，奥斯卡怪人？
All of whom have appeared in some form.
他们都以某种形式出现过。
This one will be a little looser with answers, but looks like duck and cat
这个答案会比较宽泛，但看起来鸭子和猫
were both the most popular.
都是最受欢迎的。
Duck has kind of become the mascot, suffice it to say.
可以说，鸭子已经成为吉祥物了。
Cat is kind of everywhere on CS50 social media.
猫在CS50的社交媒体上无处不在。
So we'll accept cat as well.
所以我们也接受猫。
We love Spot, but has only made that one appearance.
我们喜欢Spot，但它只出现过一次。
15,000.
15000。
Final few questions, what is the output of printf quote, unquote, "1" plus
最后几个问题，printf "1" 加
quote, unquote, "2?"
"2" 的输出是什么？
It will return an error, twelve, 3, or 12?
会返回错误，十二，3，还是12？
English and digits respectively there.
分别是英文和数字。
Six seconds.
6秒钟。
All right, one second.
好的，1秒钟。
And 12 with 74% is correct.
12，74%正确。
Because it's not quite 12, it is more rather
因为它不是完全的12，而是
1, 2 because those are two strings that got concatenated would not actually
1，2，因为这两个字符串被连接在一起，实际上不会
be an error in that case.
造成错误。
It's just not what you expect.
只是不像你预期的结果。
All right, it's getting a little harder, but still someone's
好的，越来越难了，但仍然有人
got a perfect score.
拿到了满分。
What does LIFO stand for?
LIFO代表什么？
Lost In First Order, Last In First Out, Let Inside Fall Outside,
丢失在第一顺序，后进先出，让内部掉到外面，
Long Indentation For Organization?
长缩进用于组织？
Good one.
不错。
Last In First Out, and we discussed this in the context of a stack.
后进先出，我们之前在栈的背景下讨论过这个。
Because as you pile things on top of the stack,
因为当你把东西堆放在栈顶时，
the last one in is the first one out.
最后一个进去的也是第一个出来的。
All right, nicely done, this player here.
好的，这位玩家做得很好。
Three questions to go.
还有三个问题。
On average, how early did you submit the weekly pset?
平均来说，你提前多久提交了每周的作业？
A couple of days early, no rush, the morning of, a couple of hours early,
提前几天，不着急，在早上，提前几个小时，
but was not too nervous, 11:59:59, I live on the edge.
但我没有太紧张，11:59:59，我生活在边缘。
Again, user-generated content.
再次强调，这是用户生成的内容。
And the most popular answer--
最受欢迎的答案是——
[LAUGHTER] Carter and I conferred before class
[笑声] 卡特和我课前商量了一下
and we autocratically decreed that this is
我们专断地宣布，这就是
the only right answer and the only one we
唯一正确答案，也是我们唯一
will accept here, though we appreciate the others as well.
会接受的答案，虽然我们也感谢其他答案。
Wow, all right, did you take this class for the CS50 shirt?
哇，好吧，你上这门课是为了 CS50 的 T 恤吗？
Yes, no, maybe, I'm not telling you?
是的，不，也许，我不会告诉你？
So that is this here shirt, which you'll get at the CS50 fair.
所以，这就是这件 T 恤，你将在 CS50 展览会上得到。
One second.
等一下。
And, yes, no, maybe, I'm not telling you, this time, we'll accept all four
而且，是的，不，也许，我不会告诉你，这一次，我们会接受这四个
of those, which brings us to our final question, at which point
其中所有，这让我们进入了最后一个问题，届时
we'll reveal the scores of all of our participants
我们将公布所有参与者的分数
and see if we can get the number one score online.
看看我们是否能获得在线排名第一的分数。
What is the phrase that David says at the end of each lecture?
大卫在每节课结束时说的那句话是什么？
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
[打断的声音]
DAVID MALAN: All right, before we actually
大卫·马兰：好吧，在我们实际
say what the right answer is, though we can show it,
说出正确答案之前，虽然我们可以展示出来，
Carter, we'll see that there is 98%--
卡特，我们会发现有 98% 的人——
I've never said this at the end here, but 98% answers there.
我以前从没在结尾说过，但有 98% 的答案在那里。
Let's go ahead and look at the top chart.
让我们看一下排行榜。
Do we know who web_a28c3 is?
我们知道 web_a28c3 是谁吗？
Oh my goodness, come on down.
我的天啊，快下来。
And among our friends here, can you pull up each of your scores
在我们这里的朋友中，你能拉出你们各自的分数吗？
if you're able to see?
如果你能看到？
And among our human volunteers, 16,792, 17,292, 16,958.
而我们的人类志愿者中，分别是 16,792、17,292、16,958。
So we have our human winner as well.
所以，我们的人类赢家也出现了。
So without further ado, allow me to thank our volunteers.
所以，话不多说，让我感谢一下我们的志愿者。
Thanks so much to CS50 staff.
非常感谢 CS50 的工作人员。
We're about to give out some cookies and, if you want,
我们准备发放一些饼干，如果你愿意的话，
some stress balls here.
一些减压球。
Cake is now served.
现在上蛋糕。
And this was CS50.
这就是 CS50。
[CHEERING]
[欢呼声]
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
[打断的声音]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[音乐播放]